<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ's valedictions: or sacred observations on the last words of our savior delivered on the crosse. By Jenkin Lloyd, minister of the gospel, and rector of Llandissil in Cardigan shire</title>
            <author>Lloyd, Jenkin, b. 1623 or 4.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 115 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88397</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2653</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1895_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209921</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868767</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868767</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170533</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88397)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170533)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 235:E1895[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ's valedictions: or sacred observations on the last words of our savior delivered on the crosse. By Jenkin Lloyd, minister of the gospel, and rector of Llandissil in Cardigan shire</title>
                  <author>Lloyd, Jenkin, b. 1623 or 4.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 220 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by D.M. for D. Pakeman at the Rainbow in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Seven last words --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170533:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt's Valedictions:</hi> OR SACRED OBSERVATIONS On the LAST WORDS Of our SAVIOR delivered on the CROSSE.</p>
            <p>By JENKIN LLOYD, <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel, and Rector of</hi> Llandiſſil <hi>in Cardigan ſhire</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>D. M.</hi> ſon <hi>D. Pakeman</hi> at the Rainbow in Flee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>et, 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170533:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170533:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Here preſent thee with ſuch Pious and Plain Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, as I could col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect on what our Saviour uttered on Mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> where he conſummated the grand Work of mans ſalvation through the blood of his Croſſe. Thoſe precedent ſufferings of his life, were but introductions to his laſt great Paſſion; nor did he ever produce more and greater miracles, then even in his extreme weakneſs, and when death ſeemed to be his conqueror. Miracles on earth were too low to attend a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſo high concernment,
<pb facs="tcp:170533:3"/>ſigns from heaven muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to ſeal the infinite merit of his Paſſion, which before the Jewes did moſt importunately deſire; but that tranſcended all other wonders, that when he was enthralled to the black confines of death, he moſt tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphantly returned from the furies of hell, and by an inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible power, re-enlivened his bemangled and wounded bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and adorned it with the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious dreſſes of an eternal life.</p>
            <p>And now in the heat of his great ſufferings, he ſo pierced the hearts of his perſecutors with ſuch pithy and feeling ſentences, that many of them at length returned through an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſive knowledg of their owne guiltineſs, ſtriking their breſts; and had they not ſo relented at thoſe cruelties, the very rocks
<pb facs="tcp:170533:3"/>would have ſtood up in condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of their injuſtice.</p>
            <p>The Words are in number ſeven, whereof three were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken about the ſixth hour, before the obſcuration of the ſun, which we ſhall firſt conſider, and then the other four that were delivered about the ninth hour, when God had withdrawn thoſe diſmal curtains, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enlightened that great Lumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie of heaven. For methods ſake, I uſe firſt an explanation of each word, that the true ſenſe of the holy Ghoſt may be rightly apprehended, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I do endeavour to hold forth ſuch a conſtruction, as may be moſt conducible to the glory of God, to the Analogy of Faith, the exaltation of Devotion, and the conſervation of peace and union among us; ſo that if
<pb facs="tcp:170533:4"/>happly I may in ſome things differ from others, I deſire their charity, to leave me to my liberty, if I do but differ from them, and not from fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental truths. After that I have laboured to ſatisfie thy judgment with the true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the words, my next work is, to ſtir up thy affections by laying down the conſequent duties, with proper motives to induce us to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of them: ſo that you want not thoſe Doctrines and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes that naturally flow from each Text. But becauſe in vaine doth <hi>Paul</hi> plant and <hi>Apollo</hi> water, unleſs God gives the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, I do therefore conclude each part with certain Ejacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory Prayers, pertinent to the precedent diſcourſe, that by the influence of Gods grace, the
<pb facs="tcp:170533:4"/>whole may be fruitful and ſalvifical to our ſouls, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that is the chief end for which it is expoſed to publick view, neither, as I believe, ſhall I miſs of my aim, if fear &amp; reverence attend the peruſal of the Treatiſe. Thus have you the Occaſion, Method and Scope of the Work; all that is deſired of thee, is, That having the <hi>Idaea</hi> of Chriſts charity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy thoughts (as thou ſhalt track it in each page of this Book) thou wouldſt in ſome meaſure endeavour to parallel ſo divine a pattern, and judge charitably of me the unworthy Author.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JEN. LLOYD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170533:5"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 9 line 9 <hi>read</hi> reaſon, p 10 <hi>r</hi> cloud, p 22 <hi>r</hi> by, p 51 <hi>r</hi> deliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, p 74 <hi>r</hi> that, p 77 <hi>r</hi> ſolved, p 104 <hi>r</hi> 1652, p 119 <hi>r</hi> of God, p 134 <hi>r</hi> we p 145 <hi>r</hi> Euripus, p 147 <hi>r</hi> woman, p 149 <hi>r</hi> nouriſheth, p 159 <hi>r</hi> ſeem, p 170 <hi>r</hi> hear, p 174 <hi>r</hi> accurately, <hi>ibid. r</hi> nefarious, p 180 <hi>r</hi> Sun, p 190 <hi>r</hi> occurres; p 191 <hi>r</hi> loquitur, p 204 <hi>r</hi> an Almighty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p 211 <hi>r</hi> mactatur.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170533:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chriſt's Valedictions:</hi> OR, SACRED OBSERVATIONS On the Laſt Words of our Saviour delivered on the CROSSE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The Firſt Word.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>LUKE 23.34.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Father for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them, for they know not what they do.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll Nations did ever in Nature acknowledg, not only a guiltineſs of ſin, but ſome means of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170533:6"/>to their gods in the remiſſion of ſins: For they had al ſome formal &amp; Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Sacrifices and Expiations by which they thought their ſins to be purged and waſhed away; and the people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael were preſcribed by God himſelf, what, and how to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their religious Victims: But the proper and true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory Sacrifice to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſins of the world, was only Jeſus Chriſt, the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Word of the Eternal Father, who much Coveting that Ineffable work of man's Salvation, thought it not only enough to ſuffer, but before he ſubmits himſelf to thoſe great undertakings, deemed it alſo expedient to win the hearts of the people as well by Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as Miracles. His whole
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170533:6"/>Life was a continued Lecture and Method of teaching, and becauſe the words of a dying man works commonly a great impreſſion on the affections and judgments of the hearers, therefore being now to ſeal the Leaſe of that ineſtimable purchaſe with his own blood on the Croſs, he delivered ſuch divine Legacies, ſuch Soul-livening words, as ought to ſurvive in the hearts and actions of all true Chriſtians. The firſt whereof was this, <hi>Father forgive them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</note>He called him <hi>[Father,]</hi> not God or Lord, becauſe he well knew in this condition to be needful the Benignity of a Father, not the Severity of a Judge; the Smiles of Compaſſion, not the Frowns of Juſtice. And becauſe to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170533:7"/>bend God to a Lenity (who was without doubt much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed for ſuch grand ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities) it was convenient to preſent the amiable title of a Father: the words ſeem to imply thus much, I who am thy ſuffering Son do pardon them, pardon thou alſo, O Father, their impieties, and forgive me (thy Son) this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, though they deſerve it not. Take it to thy compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Remembrance, that thou art their Father by Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and Preſervation, O then let thy Paternal favour ſhine upon them, for though they are evil, yet they are thy ſons; though they are ſinners, thou art merciful.</p>
               <p>The word <hi>[Forgive]</hi> which is the ſum of the Petition, may as well be referred to the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170533:7"/>Puniſhment as the Fault; if to the Puniſhment, this Prayer was heard, whilſt the Jews for this preſent iniquity de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved inſtant revenge, yet was it defer'd for forty years; and if in that interim they had repented, they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſafe and untouched: but becauſe they did not, God permitted an Army of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans (<hi>Veſpaſian</hi> then Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) to come againſt them, who overthrew their Head City, and deſtroyed the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Nation, ſome by the Sword, ſome by Famine, ſome ſold, the reſt Exiled into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places of the earth, as foretold by the Parable of the Vineyard, and of the Kings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting of gueſts to the marriage of his ſon,<note place="margin">Mat. 20.1</note> &amp; by the ſimilitude of the unfruitful Figtree.<note place="margin">Mat. 22.2</note> If it be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170533:8"/>referr'd to the Fault,<note place="margin">Luk. 13.6</note> the Prayer was alſo heard in that relation, for by the powerful efficacy thereof was given to many Repentance and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction of heart, in which number was the Centurion,<note place="margin">Mat. 27 54 Luk. 23 48</note> and thoſe who returned ſtrik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their guilty breſts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing him to be the Son of God.</p>
               <p>The Perſons prayed for, are either h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Manual Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, thoſe who divided his garments, or thoſe who were the effectual cauſes of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as <hi>Pilate</hi> who gave the ſentence, the people who cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, <hi>Crucifie, crucifie him,</hi> the Scribes who falſely accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him; or, as we may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend higher, the firſt man <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and his poſterity. All were involved in the Sin, all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170533:8"/>are included in the Prayer. And thou, (O my ſoul) before thou hadſt a being, the Lord foreſaw thee alſo to be ranckt ſometimes amongſt his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and thy ſelf not capable of petitioning, he prayes the Father for thee, that thy foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs be not imputed to thee.</p>
               <p>And that his interceſſion might be acceptable, he ſeems to guild the offences of his enemies with compaſſionate extenuations, as far as it might ſtand with his omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent Soveraignty, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, <hi>For they know not what they do.</hi> For certainly he could not palliate that inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in <hi>Pilate</hi> nor that cruelty in the Souldiers, nor that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie in the High Prieſt, nor that fooliſhneſs and ingratitude in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170533:9"/>the People, nor falſe Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in the Perjurers, this only remained, that he might in all excuſe their ignorance; for as the Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>If they had known it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.8</note> 
                  <hi>they had not cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified the Lord of Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Schools have made ſo many diviſions and ſub-divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Ignorance, that there goes as much learning to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Ignorance as Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg; but their ignorance in condemning the Lord of life was of a very ſtrange and tranſcendent nature<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The people knew him to be inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently condemned, and <hi>Pilate</hi> himſelf ſealed it with a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick voice,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.14 Mat. 27.24</note> 
                  <hi>I find no fault in this man, &amp;c.</hi> and, <hi>I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent of the blood of this juſt man.</hi> The Integrity of his Life declared him to be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170533:9"/>and ſin-leſs, the greatneſs of his Miracles pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed him a God, and the whole current of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets teſtified him to be the Meſſias, and yet they would not acknowledg him to be the Chriſt, the Lord of Glory: The reſon whereof is delivered by S. <hi>John,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 12.37</note> and the Prophet <hi>Iſaias, becauſe their eyes were blinded, and thoir hearts hardned, that they ſhould not ſee with their eyes, nor underſtand w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> their hearts and be converted and healed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that blindneſs proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from an Ignorance which does not excuſe, becauſe it was voluntary &amp; concomitant, not precedent. After the ſame manner are thoſe who ſin out of malice, they are alwayes infected with ſome Ignorance
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170533:10"/>which is hatch't with the ſin. The Philoſopher ſaid, <hi>Every Evil man, is an Ignorant man:</hi> And truly it may be ſpoken of all ſinners, <hi>They know not what they do:</hi> For no man covets evil as it is evil, becauſe the Object of the Will is a thing not good or ill, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (really or apparently) Good. Therefore they that make choice of evil, do chuſe it as it repreſents the Species and forms of goodneſs; yea, they apprehend it as the chiefeſt good: The cauſe of this is a perturbation of the inferiour part, which doth ſo clod and darken reaſon that it cannot rightly diſcern the Atoms of goodneſs in things coveted; for he who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits Adultery or Theft, would never affect either,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170533:10"/>were it not for the falſe good of delectation or gain which couches under Adultery or Theft, not perceiving the evil of turpitude and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice which likewiſe harbour there. So, that whoſoever ſins, is like the man, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous from a high Turret to throw himſelf headlong into ſome fierce River, ſhuts firſt his eyes, and then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits himſelf to the mercy of the Waters. He that is the Actor of evil, hates the light and labours under a pretended darkneſs, which being vincible and voluntarie does no way clear the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>But wherefore then ſerves the prayer? I anſwer, If the words be underſtood of thoſe executioners that performed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170533:11"/>only their commanded duties, and probably were ignorant as well of his Inocency as of his Divinity; or of us who were not then exiſtent, or of ſuch ſinners who knew not what was then in agitation at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> the Lord might moſt truly then Eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate theſe ſweet tones of his Compaſſion; but if they be applyed to thoſe grand contrivers and actors of that horrible treaſon, and well knew him to be the Miſſias, and an innocent man; then it is to be confeſt that Chriſts purpoſe thereby was only to extenuate the ſins of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries in the beſt manner he could; for although their Ignorance could not ſimply excuſe, yet it may have the colourable reaſon of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170533:11"/>for if they had wanted all ignorance their offence had been more grievous; and certainly if a better and more probable plea could have been found, he had willingly preſented it even for <hi>Caiphas</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> the worſt of all his enemies.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Hence may we firſt learn Chriſt's charity to be ſo Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereminent, that we may with the Apoſtle conclude, <hi>It paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all knowledge.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 3.19.</note> Neither are our tongues able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, nor our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to conceive the height of it. If any of us labour under any croſs of grief, as the pains of our teeth, our eyes, or any other member, we are ſo poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with a ſenſe of any of theſe ſufferings, that we think
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170533:12"/>on nothing elſe, nor will ſcarce admit any negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or viſits of friends; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as crucified Chriſt wore on his head a Crown of thornes, not being able to move with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exceſſive grief, nails pierced his hands and feet, from whoſe borings he drew moſt bitter pains; his naked body wearied with unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful whippings, publickly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ignominy and cold, throwing on him new ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows and new torments; yet as though he contemned thoſe cruelties and ſuffered nothing being only ſolicitous for the ſalvation of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and deſiring to avert from them an impendant dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, he preſents to his Father this mournful Obſecration, <hi>Father, forgive them, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170533:12"/>If thoſe wicked men had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered an unjuſt perſecution, what would he do? if friends, if kindred had ſuffered, not enemies, not traitors, not Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racides? His heart amongſt ſo many ſtorms of injurious ſufferings (as a Rock in the midſt of the Sea beaten with unruly waves) ſtood quiet and immoveable: after the infliction of ſo many deadly wounds, they deride his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and triumph at their evil doings; he ſpeaks not as an enemy ſtriving with his fierce adverſaries, but as a Father bemoaning his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, or a Phyſician his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents ſtrugling with a grievous diſeaſe, and preſents them to an omnipotent hand to cure their odious infirmities. This is the force of an upright cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170533:13"/>not when one is reput<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have no enemies and have peace with all men, but to live peaceably with thoſe that are haters of peace. And this is that Love the Wiſe man ſpeaks of, that many wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters cannot extinguiſh,<note place="margin">Cant. 8.7</note> nor the floods drown it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">O duri, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durati ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, quos tunta flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molliat. <hi>Bern.</hi>
                  </note>As that deluge of ſufferings could not quench the flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing charity of our Saviour, ſo the rivers of perſecution ſhould not overwhelm Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Love in his members. A whiles after there iſſued out an imitating clemency, flaming in the breſt of S. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> the Proto-martyr, which thoſe ſhowrs of ſtones could not quench, but made him break forth into that ſweet prayer,<note place="margin">Act. 7.60</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, lay not this ſin to their charge.</hi> After him
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170533:13"/>this divine virtue was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated to divers holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, who burn'd with won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful flames of charity, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the many tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of ſufferings and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions to overflow them.</p>
               <p>I may aſcend here from Chriſts Humanity to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity; great was his charity as man to his executioners, but greater it was and is as God towards men, who would war with him, and, if if they could, pluck him from heaven and Crucifie him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Who can conceive the exceeding Love of God to men altogether wicked and unthankful? God ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not the Angels in their offences,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.4</note> neither was he ſo indulgent to them as to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to repent, but men
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170533:14"/>ſinning, and blaſpheming and being deficient in their ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to him, he often ſuffers, and not only ſuffers them, but in the mean time he feeds, cheriſhes and ſupports them; (<hi>For in him we live,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 17.28</note> 
                  <hi>move, and have our being</hi>) nay, he accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulates many benefits upon them, he adorns them with wit, fattens them with riches, prefers them to honors, and ſublimes them to Kingdoms, and in the mean while he pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently expects their return from their wayes of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and perdition. Infinite are the preſidents of Gods charity towards the wicked, and enemies of his moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By this we are further taught to forgive received
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170533:14"/>Injuries, and to make our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies our friends: This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable example of Chriſt ſhould be a perſwaſive ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to draw us to it. If he as well Pardoned as Prayed for his perſecutors, why ſhould not a Chriſtian do the ſame? If God, the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who is able, both as Lord and a Judge to take a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den revenge on ſinners, yet is pleaſed to invite them to favour, and to offer them a free Pardon, why ſhould not a creature do the ſame? But you will ſay, It ſeems adverſe to the rights of Nature, that a man ſhould ſuffer himſelf to be unjuſtly trampled and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated in words or deeds, for we ſee brutiſh creatures, who are led only by an Inſtinct of Nature, ſharply on the firſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170533:15"/>ſight to encounter and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their enemies: And we have it experienced in our ſelves when by chance we eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py an adverſary, our choler kindles, our blood boyles, and there naturally ariſeth in us a thirſt of revenge. But he is altogether deceived who does thus reaſon and he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds a juſt defence with an unjuſt vindication. For, to oppoſe an offered injurie, no man forbids, but to revenge it being done, the Divine Law gain-ſaies, for that appertains not to private men, but to the publick Magiſtrate; and becauſe God is the <hi>King of Kings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 32 35 Rom. 12 19</note> therefore he proclaims it, <hi>Vengeance is mine, I will repay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beaſts which naturally ruſh upon their enemies, cannot
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170533:15"/>diſtinguiſh between Nature, and the viciouſneſs of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but man, which is beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with Reaſon, ſhould ſeparate the Nature or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which God created good, from the Vice or Sin, which is evil, and an Abortive meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proceeding from the Divel. Love the Perſon, but deteſt the injury; imitate the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſic an, who loves the Sick, but loaths the Diſeaſe; which that moſt holy <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> of all ſouls hath taught us in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.44</note> 
                  <hi>Love your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, do good to them that hurt you, bleſs them that curſe you, &amp;c. pray for them that hate you and perſecute you.</hi> The reaſon why men ſtomack their enemies, is becauſe they are brutiſh, and have a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with Beaſts: But thoſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170533:16"/>that are Spiritual, and can disband the Paſſions of the Soul, will rather compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate their enemies, and by a Chriſtian Affability win them to peace, then plot their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: To them the yoke of Chriſt is ſweet, and his burden feather-light, and his commands not heavy; but to the carnal and natural man they ſeem difficult and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty through reaſon of the predominancy of their own corruptions, and becauſe the love of God is not in them; for nothing is impoſſible to Charity, <hi>It beareth all things, believeth all things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.7</note> 
                  <hi>hopeth all things, endureth all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In holy Writ, we find how the Patriarch <hi>Joſeph</hi> in thoſe times afore the Law,<note place="margin">Gen. 45 &amp; 37</note> marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly loved his brethren, who
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170533:16"/>(as enemies) fold him to the <hi>Midianites.</hi> And how pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently <hi>David</hi> took the enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Saul</hi> who did much co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet his deſtruction;<note place="margin">1 King 4</note> yet when it was in his power to have killed him he would not. And in the law of Grace S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of himſelf and Co-Apoſtles, <hi>Being reviled,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4 12</note> 
                  <hi>we bleſſe; being perſecuted, we ſuffer; being defamed, we pray and intreat.</hi> 
                  <q>There is a known Story not imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to this purpoſe in <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus Damianus,</hi> of a man whom another moſt trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly had pulled out his eyes, and this Accident had confined him to a Monaſtry, where he lived a pure and unſpotted life, yielding all offices of charity, according to the ability of his perſon.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170533:17"/>It fell out this cruel crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture who had done this miſchievous act, ſickned of a languiſhing malady, and found himſelf enforced to be carried to that ſame place where he was whom he had bereaved of ſight: His heart gave him, He would never endure him, but for revenge put out his eyes: But contrariwiſe, the blind man being better inſtructed, upon his earneſt ſuit was deputed to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the ſick man, and he moſt willingly dedicated to him all the functions of his body, but the eyes, which the other had pulled out; and you would think him all eyes, all hands, all heart to attend this ſick man, ſo much conſideration, vigor,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170533:17"/>diligence and affection he uſed.</q> And what ſhould they here ſay, who upon the leaſt affront burn with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengful ſpirit?</p>
               <p>But it may be the objection of ſome, If we return a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit for an injurie, a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction for a curſe, the wicked would wax inſolent, and the robbers of Gods glory would become much bolder, the juſt would be oppreſſed, and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue contemned: But the caſe will prove otherwiſe, for oft times a ſoft anſwer breaks the jaws of anger,<note place="margin">Prov. 15</note> and the patience of a good man begets an admiration in the perſecutor, and by a religious Alchymy converts an enemy to a friend; neither are there wanting on the earth Political Magiſtrates, whoſe care it is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170533:18"/>according to the ſevere cords of the Laws, to bind and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the wicked to ſuch an obedience, that the juſt may lead a quiet and peaceable life. But if Humane Juſtice ſhould ſometimes ſleep, yet the Providential eyes of God are ſtill open, who never ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the evil to go unpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor the good unrewarded, and through an admirable way, when the wicked think they vex and torment the good, he makes theſe the more famous, the more illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious: <hi>Saeviſti perſecutor in Martyrem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leo. Ser. de S. <hi>Laur.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſaeviſti, &amp; aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſti palmam, dum aggeras Poenam.</hi> The Rage of a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant adds to the Glory of a Martyr; nothing made <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſo renowned as the perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his brethren.<note place="margin">Gen. 40</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170533:18"/>
               <p>Some, to avoid the ſhadow of a little diſreputation among men, and to preſerve the ſmoke of honour, will rather perſecute then forgive their enemies, thereby diſplaying themſelves to be void of true wiſdom, when as they to ſhun a leſſe evil, fall into a far greater. It is an undenyable axiome pronounced by the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Evil things may not be done, that good may come.</hi> He that receives an injury falls into the evil of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he that revengeth falls into the evil of the fault; betwixt which two there is no Symmetrical proportion, for the puniſhment makes a man but miſerable, the guilt and fault makes a man as well evil as miſerable; the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives a man of Temporal
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170533:19"/>felicity, the other robs him as well of Eternal as Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. Beſides, it is generally held an argument of a noble mind to pardon, and a ſign of a mean, &amp; Puſillanimous ſpirit to revenge. <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> that victorious Emperor of <hi>Rome,</hi> excelled more in Pardoning then Conquering his enemies, of whom <hi>Cicero</hi> gives this high Eulogie, That he forgot nothing but injuries. O, let not a Heathen under the Law of Nature ſurpaſs us in cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency and charity under the Law of Grace!</p>
               <p>But that which makes men moſt averſe from doing good and praying for their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, is, their difference about holy things. Religion, which ſhould be the grand motive to Peace and Unity, is now
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170533:19"/>become the main occaſion of ſuch rents and diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, as our Ancients never heard of, and Poſterity will ſcarce believe. The Jews were ſo infatuated in their counſels that they <hi>knew not what they did,</hi> and many of the Chriſtians are in ſuch a confuſion they know not what to hold: ſome for <hi>Paul,</hi> ſome for <hi>Apollo,</hi> ſome for they know not whom. And that which is moſt to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented is, that for ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities in opinion, they ſhould pronounce ſuch an heavy ſentence upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as is that of Damnation. If God ſhould cenſure us as we cenſure one another, I know not who ſhould be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. But my hope and praier is, That the Lord will be more
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170533:20"/>merciful to all diſſenters, then they are to one another.</p>
               <p>The ſeven Churches of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia</hi> were all the Churches of Chriſt, he walkt in the midſt of them,<note place="margin">Rev. 1.13. Chap. 2.1.</note> even in that Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm <hi>Laodicean,</hi> he held the ſeven Stars in his right hand, and though ſome were more perfect then others, yet hath he a particular charge againſt the beſt of them.<note place="margin">Chap. 2.4 14.</note> Let the Romaniſts tell us never ſo much of their unerring Chair and Infallibility, and let the Carthariſts tell us never ſo much of their Purities, yet there is no Congregation ſo ſpotleſs but Chriſt may find a blemiſh in her, no Church ſo blameleſs, but that he hath few things to urge againſt her. Let us not then judge of others, but learn to reform
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170533:20"/>our own errors; nor ſtudy how to diſpute, but to live well: to that purpoſe the Apoſtle's counſel is very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, <hi>Put on (as the elect of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 3.12 13. 14. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>holy and beloved) bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of mercy, kindneſs, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of mind, meekneſs, long ſuffering, forbearing one another, forgiving one another: If any man have a quarrel againſt any, even as Chriſt forgave you, even ſo alſo do ye: And above all things put on Charity, which is the bond of perfection, and let the peace of God rule in your hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170533:21"/>
                  <head>Ejaculations.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> THou God of Love and Peace! we are in ſuch blindneſs and diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that we know not what we think, ſpeak or do: we are at ſuch deadly few'd among our ſelves, that, like <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> we joyn together and muſter up our forces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, and all friends to Peace. Profaneneſs, Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and Ingratitude towards thee, Malice, Hatred and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge towards one another, are the reigning vices of our Times: Pardon thou thoſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170533:21"/>againſt thee, and give us grace to forgive theſe againſt our ſelves.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> We are taught (Lord) there is one fin irremiſſible,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.31 1 Joh. 5.16</note> and incapable of mercy, and therefore not to be prayed for, but being we know not who that ſinner is, and hope to find him no where, therefore we make prayers and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations for all men,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1</note> even for our enemies: We have Thee for a Preſident, and thy Word for a Precept.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Thou prayeſt their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don that are ſhedding thy blood, ſhall not we forgive thoſe that do us injuries? Thou art merciful to thy Enemies, ſhall we be cruel to our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? How grievouſly do we provoke thee every day to thy face! one of our offences
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170533:22"/>againſt thy infinite Majeſty is more then we are capable to receive from all our enemies on earth; yet how ſilently doſt thou paſs by all our hainous affronts, and bidſt thy Sun to ſhine, and thy rain to fall as well upon our grounds as thy holieſt owners? Thou doſt graciouſly invite us to thee with new mercies, and do we call our ſelves the ſons of that Father whom we will not imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate? Do we daily pray to thee, To forgive us as we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give others, whiles we reſolve to forgive none whom we can plague with revenge?</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Shall we hear a <hi>Cato</hi> ſay, That he could and did pardon all offenders but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? and ſhall we pardon none but our ſelves? Shall a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan without God have ſuch
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170533:22"/>rule over his Paſſion? and ſhall a Chriſtian, who profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a more divine Phyloſophy give the reins to the wild and unruly erruptions of his rage?</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5.</hi> And what (Lord) though we differ in Judgments, yet let us not vary in Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions? What though our Brains be diverſe, yet let our Hearts be one?</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6.</hi> We all believe in thee (O God) and in the ſame Chriſt, and are all Baptized into him, and look to be ſaved by his ſufferings. We agree in that one and only Foundation; we all embrace the two Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and as I hope, the three Creeds, and many other very material points; why ſhould we vary about the ſuperſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures and circumſtantials of Religion?</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170533:23"/>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7.</hi> We believe thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to be of that extent,<note place="margin">Act. 2.21 Rom. 10.13</note> that whoſoever ſhall call upon thy Name ſhall be ſaved; why ſhould we then be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable as to exclude ſo many millions of weak, but true believers out of the Church below, or out of heaven above, for no other reaſon but becauſe they are not of our judgments in all things?</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8.</hi> VVhile we thus cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and aſſault each other, what advantages we give to our common adverſary, who takes pleaſure to ſee us bickering with our ſelves? And how far are we from that. Legacy of thy Son, that true. Love he recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to his Diſciples? Lord, then, we pray thee,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170533:23"/>glew our hearts together by the grace of thy holy Spirit, and purge our of them all the droſſe and dregs of hatred, malice, ſchiſm and hereſie.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9.</hi> If it muſt be with us as with thoſe two famous Rivers of the Eaſt, the <hi>Sava</hi> and the <hi>Danuby,</hi> that runne together threeſcore miles in one channel with their waters divided in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry colour from each other, yet let it be (as it is in them) without noiſe, without violence.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10.</hi> Keep us from Satan, the Spirit of Diviſion, grant that we may live as Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of thy family, Doves of thy flock, and Lambs of thy fold, by forgetting and forgiving all that is ſpoke
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170533:24"/>or done againſt us. Make us all (Lord) the ſons of Peace, even for his ſake who is the Prince of Peace, Jeſus Chriſt our Lord! <hi>Amen!</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170533:24"/>
               <head>The Second Word.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>LUKE 23.43.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Verily, I ſay unto thee, This day thou ſhalt be with me in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He occaſion of the Word, is this, When two Theeves were Crucified with our Saviour, one on the right hand, the other on the left; the one aggravating his former ſins did blaſpheme Chriſt, and objected unto him an Imbecility,<note place="margin">Ver. 39.</note> 
                  <hi>If thou be the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170533:25"/>Chriſt, ſave thy ſelf and us;</hi> the other defended him, and gives this modeſt check to the blaſphemer, <hi>Feareſt thou not God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 40</note> 
                  <hi>being thou art in the ſame condemnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the other Evangeliſts ſeem to affirm the two theeves to be guilty of blaſphemy,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.44 Mar. 15.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> how then doth <hi>Luke</hi> ſpeak but of one?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> l <hi>3</hi> de Conſenſu E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang. c. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves the doubt thus, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> do take there the number of multitude, for the number ſingular, as it is frequent in holy Writ: And ſo the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the Prophets,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.33, 37</note> 
                  <hi>how they ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the mouth of Lions, how they were stoned, they were hewn aſunder, how they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred up and down in Sheep skins, and in Goats skins.</hi> And notwithſtanding, he
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170533:25"/>which ſtopt the mouth of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was only <hi>Daniel,</hi> and he that was ſtoned was only <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> and he that was hewen aſunder was only <hi>Iſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as.</hi> Some think the good thief to have changed his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion upon the hearing of Chriſt preſenting thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate ſpeeches to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Father, forgive them, &amp;c.</hi> But <hi>Luke</hi> doth evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare thoſe words to be delivered before the wicked thief began to blaſpheme; and this alſo is conſonant to the judgment of another Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Church,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> in Luc. 23</note> who ſaith, One only to have blaſphem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the other to have as well praiſed as defended Chriſt, and therefore rebukes the ſauſineſs of his companion, <hi>Feareſt thou not God? &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170533:26"/>
               <p>Happy thief! as well in regard of his fellowſhip in ſuffering with a Saviour, as of that divine light which began to open it ſelf thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; he was no ſooner converted himſelf, but he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to make a Proſelite of his brother. And then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in a good work, and thoſe ſparkles of grace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing in his now happy Soul, he confeſſeth his own ſins,<note place="margin">Ver. 41.</note> and preacheth the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of Chriſt; <hi>And we, truly, are juſtly condemned to the death of the Croſſe, for we receive things worthy of what we have done, but this man hath done nothing amiſſe.</hi> Afterwards the Sun of illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating Glory ſhining more brightly on him, his Soul breaks forth into thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> holy
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170533:26"/>Ejaculation, <hi>Lord, remember me when thou comeſt into thy Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold, with what an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confidence he preſents his Petition! He whom <hi>Peter</hi> thrice denied, this poor Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent openly confeſſed, and called him Lord. <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle denies to believe unleſs he could feel Chriſt; the thief but beholding him miſerably tortured on the Croſs, proclaims him boldly (and in the face of his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries) an heir apparent to a Kingdom. He confeſſed him a Lord whom he beholds na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, wounded, grieved and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly derided; and he ſtiles him a King when there was no probability of reigning in him; for Kings only reign while they live, (and ſome
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170533:27"/>ſcarce ſo long) but when they leave off their weed of Mortality, they part with their robe of Majeſty.</p>
               <p>Neither doth he petition for any thing in particular, but only to <hi>Remember him. .i.</hi> If Chriſt did but caſt a thought on him, and glance but the gracious eye of his favour towards him, it were a plenary conſummation of all his deſires, becauſe he was fully aſſured of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, goodneſs and charity.</p>
               <p>But what Kingdom is here underſtood? Not that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Kingdom on earth which the Jews expected, and yet he had a title to reign o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, and was of the blood Royal of Iſrael, and therefore the Wiſemen after his Nativity made this enquiry
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170533:27"/>
                  <hi>Where is he that is born King of the Jews?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 2</note> And himſelf told <hi>Pilate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 18.37</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſaiſt that I am a King, for this cauſe am I born, and for this cauſe came I into the world, that I ſhould bear witneſs unto the truth.</hi> But though he was a King in the world, yet was he not pleaſed to exerciſe his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, but lived as a Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim among enemies, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, inſtead of honours due to a Royal perſon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and reproach. But the Kingdom here meant, is that Spiritual and Eternal one in the heavens; that, where there is a perfect Beatitude of the ſoul, by which man is free from all ſervitude, and the ſubjection of things cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, and ſubject only to God, whom to ſerve is to reign:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170533:28"/>And that which is intimated in the Parable of a <hi>certain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lu's. 19.12.</note> 
                  <hi>that went into a ſtrange Country to receive for himſelf a Kingdom, and ſo to come again.</hi> That is, Chriſt was to paſs by the weariſom ſteps of a bitter death to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life, there to receive a glorious Diadem, and then to return in the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to render every man according to his works.</p>
               <p>And that Kingdom, as much as appertained to the Beatitude of the ſoul, Chriſt indeed had from his very Conception, but what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to his body he had it not <hi>de facto,</hi> or in a glorious actualitie (but <hi>de jure</hi> and in an honourable inheritance) until after his Reſurrection; for while he ſojourned on
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170533:28"/>earth he was ſubject to all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane infirmities (ſin only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) yea, to death it ſelf; but there belonged to him a true glorious body, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death he was to enjoy: for ſo he teſtifieth of himſelf, <hi>It behoved Chriſt firſt to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 24.26</note> 
                  <hi>and then to enter into his Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo it is for this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Glory that this Thief prayes for; his cravings are not temporal or carnal, but his divine and new-faſhioned ſoul aims at things Sempi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and ſublime, which makes Chriſt more compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his deſires, for he had no ſooner ended his humble and ſhort Petition, but behold a gracious return and grant; <hi>Verily, I ſay unto thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He begins his anſwer with
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170533:29"/>a ſolemn word [<hi>Amen,</hi> or <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily</hi>] a word which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour uſed in any thing which tended to a ſerious concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> Tract <hi>41</hi> in Joan</note> it hath the propriety of an oath: and the reaſons why he uſes this importunate manner of ſpeaking is, becauſe the thief might well doubt of the promiſe, were it not for this earneſt aſſeveration.
<list>
                     <item>1. In regard of his own perſon, which could not ſeem any way worthy of ſo bleſſed a reward, or ſo rich a bleſſing. For who could imagin ſo bad a liver to paſs ſo ſpeedily from the Croſs to a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom?</item>
                     <item>2. In regard of Chriſts preſent condition, for then he was the miſerable Character of poverty, weakneſs, and all ſorts of humane Calamities. And he might thus argue, If
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170533:29"/>he be not able whileſt he lives to perform good offices for his friends, how can he beſtow them being dead? This might have been his carnal reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</item>
                     <item>3. And then in regard of the thing promiſed, Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, which was then known to belong to the body only, not to the ſoul.</item>
                  </list> So is the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymologie of it according to the Hebrew, An earthly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe. It had been more credible if Chriſt had ſaid, To day thou ſhalt be with me in the place of Joy, with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Jſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi> Therefore being ſo many ſcruples might occur unto this new convert, Chriſt, to remove them all, confirms the the verity of his anſwer with this ſerious Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:170533:30"/>
               <p>And his paſſage to Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe was but ſhort, not a daies journey: He does not ſay, In the day of Judgment thou ſhalt be placed on the right hand with the Juſt; nor does he ſay, (with the Millenari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) after a thouſand years ſleep thy ſoul ſhall enjoy the pleaſures of heaven; nor doth he ſay, Thou muſt firſt be refined in the Romiſh Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory; or after ſome months or daies be beatified (and that had been a happineſſe beyond his expectation or merit) but, this day, this very hour, thou ſhalt tranſmigrate with me from the Tree of the Croſs, to the Joyes of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</p>
               <p>Though it be Controvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſome, what is here meant by Paradiſe, yet it is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170533:30"/>the opinion of very Orthodox Divines, That Chriſt the day after his death, was with his Body in the grave, and with his Soul triumphing on the infernal Spirits in hell: but to neither of theſe can the name of Paradiſe be aſſigned; the grave being but a gloomy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle for dead bodies; (where Chriſt's body only could be lay'd.) and under hell is intimated a place of torments. But Paradiſe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a Garden of delight; in the Terreſtrial one there were flouriſhing Trees, fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Waters, Salubrietie of air, and all the variety of deliouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that <hi>Adam</hi> could enjoy: And in the Celeſtial one there are glorious and immortal Joyes, frnitions of endleſſe Beatitude, an inacceſſible
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170533:31"/>light, Seats and Manſions for the bleſſed. The firſt was Local and Tranſient, this is Spiritual and Eternal: The joyes of the other were Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral; the Soul is Beatified in the latter by virtue of the Beatifical viſion of God. And this heavenly Paradiſe Chriſt promiſed the thief, and that he would be with him; and ſo he was according to his Divinity. According to his Humane nature, he was part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the grave and partly in hell, untill the third day, upon which he aſcended in a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and triumphant manner into heaven. But according to the Divine (as he was God) he had an Ubiquitary Being, he was then and alwayes in Heaven, Paradiſe, and all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.13</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170533:31"/>
               <p>Therefore very proper were the words of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our when he ſaith not, This day thou ſhalt be with me in my Kingdom, becauſe that day Chriſt was not to receive his Kingdom, that is, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect felicity of Body and Soul, till after his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when he was to have a body glorious, immortal, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſible, ſubject to no ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude or infirmity: (neither was the thief to enjoy this fellowſhip until the general day of Judgment) but in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, becauſe that day there was a community of glory to his ſoul, and thoſe of all true Saints. And this is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and eſſential felicity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Heavenly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe. Neither doth Chriſt ſay, We ſhall be there, for he
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170533:32"/>was then, and before that time there, according to the ſuperiour portion of his ſoul; but <hi>thou ſhalt be with me there,</hi> that is, even thy Soul ſhal alſo really be, where now actually my divine Soul is; <hi>.i.</hi> In the bleſſed joyes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Learn hence, O man!</p>
               <p n="1">1. How great and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is the mercy and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of Chriſt towards all his ſervants? He, being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt with ſorrows might not have heard the Religious thief; but his charity had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be inſenſible of his own torments, then not to give ear to a miſerable ſinner, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing his delinquencies. He was ſilent altogether at the maledictions and revilings of the Prieſts and Souldiers, but to the humble clamours of a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170533:32"/>poor penitent, he could not chooſe but give a gracious Audience. He was ſilent at their Execrations, becauſe he was Patient, and he was open-cared to the thief's Petition, becauſe he was Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that ſerve Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Lords do labour much, but the rewards of their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices are commonly far ſhort of their expectations; and we might obſerve many who have ſpun out their times in the Courts of Princes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home in their declining age either meer Mendicants, or unregarded: But this Holy Prince, and Preſident of true Liberality, received nothing from this Peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial ſervant, but a few good words, and deſires of ſerving
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170533:33"/>him; and behold, what a Boon he confers upon him? that very day he granted him a free pardon of all the ſins he had committed in the whole courſe of his wicked life. Then he prefers him to <hi>Abrahams</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſom, to a Quire of Saints an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Angels; Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs and Prophets were made his Aſſociats, and he himſelf made partaker of that Heavenly happineſſe which is Undefinable and Eternal. We read that the Roman Emperors gave vaſt treaſures, ſometimes whole Provinces and Kingdoms to their Minions, but this Prince beſtowed on his new favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite more then they could either reach or conceive. Neither was this goodneſs of Chriſt peculiar to this poor
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170533:33"/>delinquent; his Apoſtles de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted their ſmall veſſels, their nets and cottages to ſerve him, and then he appointed them Princes over the earth, he ſubjected to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands Divels, Serpents,<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.2, 3 Mat. 10 8</note> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and Powers, and all ſorts of Diſeaſes. And he promiſes to all that ſhall leave their neareſt relations for his ſake, and part with their deareſt enjoyments for his ſervice, a hundred fold, that is, a reward incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly greater then thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, to wit, Spiritual joys and bleſſings in this world, and life Eternal in that to come. We might reflect our thoughts on what great things the Lord wrought for Martyrs and Confeſſors of former ages, how they came
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170533:34"/>to honour by ignominy, to riches by poverty, to great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by the infamous puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Croſs, to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality by a bloody death; and how he would ſtill honor them that honor him. What fools then are thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh Chriſt, the giver of all goodneſs, and ſacrifice to Mammon, the author of all evil?</p>
               <p n="2">2. We have here alſo repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto us the power of Gods Grace, and the Imbeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Humane Will; This good thief was a remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſinner, and perſevered ſo even to the puniſhment of the Croſs, and in ſo eminent danger of Damnation, there was none preſent that could afford him either the ſolace of advice or aſſiſtance: For
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170533:34"/>though he was moſt near the Saviour of the world, yet he heard the high Prieſts and Phariſees affirming him to be a ſeducer, ambitious, and an uſurper of anothers King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and he heard his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thief (as it were) bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at him, and there was none that beſtowed a word of comfort on him or Chriſt; but behold the prevalency of Divine Grace! when he was thus bereft of all humane aid, and ſeemed to have no hope of Salvation, being on the next ſtep to perdition, the Spirit of God ſhined on him in a miraculous manner, and in an inſtant ſo beautified and changed his heart, that upon a ſudden he confeſſed Chriſt to be an innocent ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer, and the King of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170533:35"/>world to come; and checkt his preſumptuous companion and perſwaded him to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and before the ſtaring multitude committed himſelf to the protection of a dying Saviour. Whereas the other Malefactor (in whom is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed to life humane infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie) was not at all moved at the ſtrangeneſs of thoſe accidents; not at the charity of Chriſt, who prayed for his perſecutors, nor at his extreme ſufferings, nor at the admonition and example of his fellow thief, nor at the unwonted darkneſs, nor at the cleaving of the Rocks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, nor at thoſe who through juſt aſtoniſhment re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home ſtriking their breſts (all which hapned af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the converſion of the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170533:35"/>good thief) yet was he not at all changed though he had the helps of ſo many perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding arguments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But why was the one inſpired at that inſtant with ſaving Grace, the other not? both were equally great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners before that time, and but one now a Saint?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> No other reaſon can be aſſigned, then why God loved <hi>Jacob</hi> and hated <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau?</hi> but becauſe it was the will of God: we muſt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with that. All other reaſons are ſhut up in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Ark of God, which we muſt rather admire in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine honor and humble ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, then endeavour to unlock or touch. <hi>Shall the thing formed ask the Potter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 9.80.</note> 
                  <hi>Why haſt thou thus faſhioned
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170533:36"/>me? Shall not the Creator of all, make ſome veſſels of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſome veſſels of diſhonour, yet all to his glory?</hi> which is as much manifeſted in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the bad, as the ſalvation of the good. There can be no iniquity with him, for though his judgments are occult, yet are they not unjuſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But this Caution we are farther taught by the words: Though we muſt embrace the example of the holy thief in our Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet not in our Imitation. It may miniſter this comfort to a ſad and deſpairing Soul, That God hath and can par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don a true penitent be his ſins never ſo great; but it muſt not lead us to defer our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance until the utmoſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170533:36"/>of our lives. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of <hi>Saul</hi> the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and this thief upon the Croſs, is become <hi>Proverbium Peccatorum,</hi> the Sinners Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, and ſerves him,<note place="margin">Gregor.</note> and ſatisfies him in all caſes. But thou preſumptuous ſinner that putteſt off thy amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon confidence of theſe examples, doſt but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude thine own Soul: It is not ſafe concluding out of ſingle inſtances, there is much diſparity between thy caſe and this thief's.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thy time is not the ſame: When thou canſt find ſuch another day, look for ſuch another mercy; A day that cleft the grave-ſtones of dead men; A day that rent the Temple it ſelf; A day that the Sun durſt not ſee;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170533:37"/>A day that ſaw the Soul of Chriſt depart from his body; there ſhall be no more ſuch dayes, therefore preſume not of that.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Beſides, thou maiſt look at the thief as on a Turk or Heathen newly entred into Chriſtianity, Baptized from ſin, Confirmed by Chriſt, ſo dying and ſaved; but how often haſt thou broke thy Baptiſmal vows? and with <hi>Copronimus</hi> defiled thy Font,<note place="margin">Eccl. Hiſt.</note> by rejecting thoſe means which God hath given thee to ſecure thy intereſt and hopes of heaven.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The thief was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted at laſt but at firſt;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyril.</hi> Non in fine ſed in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eipio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro.</note> as ſoon as God afforded him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Call he came. But to how many calls haſt thou ſtopt thine ears? O ſinful man!
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170533:37"/>How often hath God called thee with a voice of Terror? by Thunder and Lightning, by Wars, Plagues, Famine and other Judgments? How often hath he ſweetly called thee by the pleaſant promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Goſpel, by the motions of his Spirit, and by the temporal bleſſings of peace and plenty? Thou ſhalt find here that although it hapned to one to receive Grace in his very laſt gaſp (which was a Miracle of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, a Prodigie of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence) yet the other found his judgment; the one Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the other Blaſphemed; ſo the one was Saved, the other was loſt. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall peruſe Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Sacred or Humane, and obſerve Quotidian events,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170533:38"/>ſhall find very few to end their dayes well, that have looſly ran the whole courſe of their lives. And as they can hardly eſcape the furie of a Divine Juſtice that have acted a negligent and a vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life, ſo there are but few after a life well ſpun, but die in Gods fear and are made partakers of his Glory.</p>
               <p>Begin then betimes, O man, to become a new man!<note place="margin">n="*" Omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m crede diem, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ibi delux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum. <hi>Hor.</hi>
                  </note> make every day thy laſt day, that thy laſt may be happy. The <hi>Indian</hi> Gym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſophiſts cauſed their graves to be made before their gates, that at their ingreſs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs they might be put in mind of their laſt day; and happy were we if in the daies of our youth and vanity we ſpent ſome time in the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170533:38"/>of our Mortalitie, and of the account we are to make at the day our Souls and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are divorced: For that day may be ſudden, and give us no time; or diſtracted, and take away our ſenſes; or curſed, and keep away Grace. <hi>Chryſologus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gregor.</note> a man as full of ſin as he was of wealth, being on his death-bed in a bitter Agony cryed out, <hi>Inducius veluſque mane,</hi> truce but till the morning! and with thoſe very words breathed his laſt. 'Tis not a tear or a groan then can expiate the ſins of a whole life, nor <hi>every one that ſaith, Lord, Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7.21.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall enter into the Kingdom of heaven, but he that doth the will of our Father which is in heaven.</hi> Let theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons then move thee further
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170533:39"/>to avoid all delayes in prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy ſelf againſt the laſt day:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The uncertainty of its time: It was the policy of <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> never to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint his Army aforehand with the time of their march, that they might be ready on all occaſions; and ſuch is the wiſdom of our God that he hath concealed this day from us, that we might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſtand upon our guard and be ready.</p>
               <p n="2">2 No time is ſecure: As no place, no Sanctuary can exempt us from deaths ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach (it may come to us in the Church, in the Street, in our beds, &amp;c.) ſo no time can priviledge from its arreſt; in the night as well as in the day, in youth as well as in old age.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170533:39"/>
               <p n="3">3. Sometimes when men leaſt think of it it comes: Whilſt the Crocodile ſleeps the<note place="margin">n="*" A kind of a Rat.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cknewmon getteth in and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eateth his bowels; whileſt the <hi>Theban</hi> Centinel was nodding, Gen. <hi>Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nondas</hi> came and thruſt him through.</p>
               <p n="4">4. All the time alotted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that day is little enough for ſo great a work: We have ſcarce time to learn how to live well, ſaith the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, but we are ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with time to learn the art of dying well, ſaith the Divine.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Thy Preparation for, will be no Acceleration of the day: Our death will not be the nearer but ſweeter, the blow will not come the ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er foreſeen,<note place="margin">Premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti mali ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ictas.</note> but it will be the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170533:40"/>eaſier; thy life and death will be the more comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That day will be moſt diſmal and Exitial to all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared perſons; like that of the man, whom when the King came in found without a wedding garment, who was bound hand and foot and caſt into utter darkneſs.<note place="margin">Mat. 22.13</note> Oh! that any, or all of theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations might awaken our ſecurity, and keep us from ſleeping in thoſe ſins which will deprive us of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170533:40"/>
                  <p>LORD, We admire the deepneſs of the riches of thy mercy and goodneſs, who wouldſt condeſcend to be thus ignominiouſly tortured between two grand Malefactors for our ſakes: How thou didſt abaſe thy ſelf for our pride, and humble thy ſelf on earth to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance us to glory?</p>
                  <p>Teach us, Lord, who are but duſt and aſhes to be lowly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, and never to exalt our ſelves before or againſt thee, leaſt by our pride we be excluded (with the Angels) out of Heaven, or (with Man) out of Paradiſe.</p>
                  <p>But among all thy Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170533:41"/>we moſt extol thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which was ſo tranſcendent to this poor penitent thief, whom thou didſt reſcue from the jaws of hell through thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Merits.</p>
                  <p>It had been enough (O God) if thou hadſt but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him to be with thee: for where had been ill with thee? or where had it been well without thee? but thou haſt crowned him with bliſs and glory in the higheſt heavens.</p>
                  <p>By this we are taught (Lord) not to deſpair of thy Clemency, for though Cherubins keep thy Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and thy gate of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy be guarded by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, yet thou haſt opened the door of it to as very ſinners as our ſelves.</p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170533:41"/>
                  <p>Though we have ſinnes more numerous then the ſands of the ſea, or the ſtars of the firmament, yet is thy mercy more and above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. No ſtains or guilts can make us ſo vile but thy Sons blood can waſh them off: <hi>David, Peter, Magdalen, Paul</hi> and this good thief were cured by the power of that mercie, and virtue of that blood.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe (Lord) we are too prone to preſume of thy mercy, which is ſo eminent over al thy works, we therefore entreat thee to keep us from carnal ſecurity, from a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargy in ſin, and the delayes of all religious duties.</p>
                  <p>When ever we fall into ſin, do thou (Lord) by thy Grace raiſe us up to a newneſs of life, to a true and timely repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170533:42"/>leſt we ſleep and lie in our iniquities until we feel the horror of eternal death. Raiſe us with <hi>David</hi> from the ſin of wilfulneſs, with <hi>Peter</hi> from thoſe of infirmity, &amp; with <hi>Paul</hi> from thoſe of ignorance.</p>
                  <p>Thou calledſt this penitent but once and he obeyed thy voice, repented, and was ſaved, but (Lord) how often are we called? how often wouldſt thou have gathered us (as a hen doth her chickings) under thy wings, but we would not!</p>
                  <p>O grant then, that me may be either allured by thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, or terrified by thy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or converted by thy Word, or won by thy Spirit, that we may hate ſin and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake it, love thee and never leave thee until thou haſt brought us to that heavenly
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170533:42"/>Paradiſe where thy Saints and Angels ſing daily Halalujahs to thy bleſſed Name. Grant this, Father of Mercies and God of Grace, even for his ſake who ſuffered with ſinners, and dyed for our ſins, Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:170533:43"/>
               <head>The Third Word.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>JOHN 19.26, 27</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>He ſaith unto his mother, Woman, behold thy Son, and to the Diſciple, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy Mother.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Queſtion is here to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſt, Why S. <hi>John</hi> did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the three women to have ſtood near the Croſs of the Lord, when S. <hi>Mark</hi> 15.40. and S. <hi>Luke</hi> 23.49. write they ſtood afar
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170533:43"/>off? But this is ſoon ſalved;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>S. Aug.</hi> lib. <hi>3</hi> de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. Evang.</note> they may be ſaid to have ſtood afar off in relation of the guard and ſouldiers who did even touch the Croſs; near, becauſe they could ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily hear Chriſt. Or they may be ſaid to have ſtood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far off at the inſtant of Crucifixion, the multitude hindring them, but when his ſuffering began to be comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, many giving way, they might make a nearer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach.</p>
               <p>The ſum of the words is this, Being I am now to paſs from this loathſome world to my glorious Father, and knowing thee to be deſtitute of all humane aſſiſtances, I commend thee to my moſt loving Diſciple <hi>John,</hi> he ſhall be to thee a Son, and thou
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170533:44"/>ſhalt be to him a Mother. The command was moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to them both, and S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of himſelf in the following words, <hi>and from that hour the Diſciple took her home.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But S. <hi>John</hi> was one of them who by his Maſters mandate had relinquiſhed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother, all relations and poſſeſſions to follow Chriſt, how comes he now, having forſaken his own, to take the charge of another mother?<note place="margin">Mat. 4.22</note> The reſolve is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; The Apoſtles that they might follow Chriſt, diſmiſt father and mother as they were a hindrance to the preaching of the Goſpel, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in regard of carnal af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, or worldly commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, but in what concerned
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170533:44"/>their care and ſolemn duty they left them not; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was committed to him, having no other viſible worldly ſupport. God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mans aſſiſtance, could by the adminiſtration of Angels have procured her a lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and protection, but it was our Saviours pleaſure to have it done by <hi>John,</hi> as well in regard of an honour to him, as a love to her. God ſent <hi>Elias</hi> to be fed by a widow, not that he could no longer feed him by Crows as formerly, but by this action he ſeemed to vouchſafe a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the widow; ſo it pleaſed the Lord to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his mother to this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>S. Aug:</hi> Serm. <hi>26</hi> de Verb. Domini.</note> to demonſtrate it was both a remarkable bleſſing
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170533:45"/>to him, and that he loved him above the reſt; and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change was happy, when in lieu of a mother, the wife of a Fiſher, he took the mother of a Saviour, the beſt of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, full of grace, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in her Sex.</p>
               <p>But,</p>
               <p n="1">1. He that diligently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves may gather hence, Chriſts deſires to ſuffer for our ſalvation to be infinite and inexpreſſible, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our redemption might be moſt full and copious. Other men think it an augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their ſorrows to have their kindred, friends and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liances ſpectators of their death, eſpecially of that which is violent and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous; but Chriſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with his own real paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170533:45"/>which was moſt cruel and full of diſhonour, would have his Mother and this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to be alſo preſent, that the Sympathetical ſorrows of his deareſt might add to, and reduplicate his own perſonal ſufferings. Three <hi>Maries</hi> and a Diſciple ſtood near the place of his ſufferings, that as four Fountains of blood iſſued from his body on the Croſs, ſo from their mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful eyes might ſpring four Fountains of tears; ſo that it is queſtionable, whether he felt more ſorrow for the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his own blood, or their tears. Methinks I hear Chriſt bemoaning himſelf, The ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſows of death have compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me,<note place="margin">Pſal. 17.9</note> but the ſword fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by <hi>Simeon</hi> which ſhould pierce the ſoul of my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent<note place="margin">Luk. 2.35</note>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170533:46"/>mother, doth as much Lacerate and wound my heart. Moſt bitter death! that ſeparate not only the ſoul from the body, but alſo a Mother, and ſuch a Mother from ſuch a Son!</p>
               <p>God ſo loved the world that he gave his only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son for the Redemption of it, and he ſo loved the Father, that for his honour Rivelets of blood ſtreamed from him, that we ſhould not periſh but have everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life: Yet we give ſuch a diſobedient reſiſtencie to his goodneſs, that we had rather be confounded in the juſt fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of an omnipotent God, then taſt the ſweetneſs of his compaſſion. One drop of his moſt precious blood might have been a ſufficient Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170533:46"/>for the Redemption of more worlds, and yet he would ſacrifice all for this one, thereby as well to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dear us, as fully to ſatisfie the juſtice of his Father.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But there are many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations that ariſe from a myſtery of the three women that ſtood near the Croſs. Some out of a petulan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of wit, to maintain Paradoxes and ſuch ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities, have called in queſtion the abilities and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of women, in the Root thereof, in the Reaſonable and Immortal Soul; but no man of Piety and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Scripture can admit ſuch a doubt. Here are wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that were ſedulous and conſtant in their religious of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170533:47"/>to our Saviour to the laſt gaſp:<note place="margin">Mat. 28.6</note> and after that he was interred, they came with a pious intention to ſee the Sepulchre, and out of a civil reſpect to embalm his body in the Monument where they thought to find it. When others (even his own Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) through timer ouſneſſe and infidelity had deſerted their Maſter, theſe (like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable friends) followed him to his grave, and would not reſt there till an Angel of heaven had aſſured them of his Reſurrection. The zeal and piety of women have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualled, if not ſurpaſſed the beſt of men; S. <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies in their behalf, that they were great inſtruments for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing of true Religion. At <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 17.4.</note> 
                  <hi>of the chief
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170533:47"/>women not a few;</hi> great, and many. Neither do we read of any woman in the Goſpel that aſſiſted the perſecutors of Chriſt, or furthered his afflictions, even <hi>Pilats</hi> wife diſſwaded it. <hi>Jerome</hi> writ many letters to divers holy Ladies, for the moſt part all of one Stock and kindred, and all ſo Religious, as that he ſayes, If <hi>Jupiter</hi> were their Couſin and of their kindred, he believes <hi>Jupiter</hi> would be a Chriſtian; he would leave being ſuch a god, as he was, to be their fellow ſervant to the true God. Woman, as well as Man was made after the image of God in the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; and in the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her ſex ſhall not diminiſh her glory. Of which ſhe receives one fair beam and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170533:48"/>inchoation at the Paſſion of Chriſt, that women continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their attendance on him to the laſt, and that by the miniſtry of Angels the glad tidings of his Reſurrection was communicated to them before any other.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And becauſe they were worthy to be known, the Holy Ghoſt celebrates them by their names and qualities; we will therefore conſider who they were and what they were, their Names firſt; and then their Conditions. There is an Hiſtorical relation and obſervation,<note place="margin">Badin <hi>de Repub.</hi> l. 6 c. 4</note> That in divers Kingdoms in Europe the Crown did fall at one time upon women of one name, <hi>Mary.</hi> It was ſo in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, Denmark,</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170533:48"/>and <hi>Hungaria,</hi> all four <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi> Here we have but three, <hi>Mary Magdalen, Mary</hi> the wife of <hi>Cleophas,</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> the Virgin, and yet ſuch three as wear now Immortal Crowns in Heaven. Indeed it is a Noble and a Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive Name, <hi>Mary.</hi> It is the Name of woman in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, according to ſome of the Learned;<note place="margin">Gen. 2.23</note> for when <hi>Adam</hi> ſayes of <hi>Eve, She ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Woman,</hi> in the Arabick Tranſlation, there is this name, <hi>She ſhall be called Mary;</hi> and the Arabick is perchance a Dialect of the Hebrew. But in pure and Original Hebrew the word ſignifies <hi>Exaltation,</hi> and whatſoever is beſt in the kind thereof; and worthily are they to be ever exalted for
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170533:49"/>their diligence and perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in their devotion. This is alſo like, if not the ſame, as <hi>Miriam,</hi> the ſiſter of <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> that with her Quire of women aſſiſted at that Euchariſtical Sacrifice, that triumphant Song of thankſgiving upon the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and ſubverſion of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> in the red Sea.<note place="margin">Exo. 15.20</note> As <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> and <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the ſame to men, ſo <hi>Miriam</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> is the ſame name in wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men according to ſome. The word denotes <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> not only in Power but in Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And great are they in the eyes of God, and to be magnified by men to all Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But we intend not to dwell upon this circumſtance,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170533:49"/>but paſs to another conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable that ſprings from the Quality of the women, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to their Spiritual ſtate. We find <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> perſonates the penitent or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipient, the other <hi>Mary,</hi> the proficient, the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> thoſe who are perfect. All three had need of Chriſt, and to ſtand near the banner of the Croſs. The Incipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents that are to war with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſins and concupiſcences, want the guidance and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of ſo great a General as Chriſt, that beholding him ſtruggling with ſo ſubtil and malicious an enemy as the old ſerpent, and openly triumphing over him, they might be animated to fight the Lords battel againſt all the aſſaults of the divel, and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170533:50"/>not to deſiſt untill they have obtained an honourable vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory. The Proficients (who are repreſented by <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Cleophas,</hi> who was a married woman, and a mother of ſons) had need of him too, leaſt the cares and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſs of this world ſhould choake the good ſeed ſown in their hearts. Chriſt not content with good works (many and great) which he had formerly done, aſcends by the Croſs to higher, and deſcends not from thence, till he beholds a vanquiſhed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my proſtrate at his feet. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more hurts a Profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, then when he languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in his courſe, and ſtifles his proceedings; according to that old Moral. In the way of Virtue, not to go on, is
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170533:50"/>to go backward,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> ad Ganinum.</note> as <hi>Bernard</hi> doth rightly exemplifie in an Epiſtle, in which he produces an inſtance of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, where all do either aſcend or deſcend, none keeps a fixt ſtation. Thoſe alſo who are Perfect and Virgins, as <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were (and for that cauſe the more beloved of our Saviour) I ſay thoſe do much need the aſſiſtances of Chriſt's ſufferings; for they are in an higher condition, and ought much to fear the tympanies and ſwellings of pride and ſelf-conceit, which can no better way be aſſwag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and taken down, then by looking into the glaſs of the Croſs. There they may find an admirable preſident of true humility, even Omnipotency it ſelf yielding to moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170533:51"/>ſufferings: He, in whom are all the treaſures of wiſdom and knowledg,<note place="margin">Col 2.3</note> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits himſelf to be illuded and reputed may by <hi>Herod</hi> and his armie: He that ſits between the Cherubims, and can blaſt a ſtar with a breath,<note place="margin">Pſal. 99.1</note> and melt a Church with a look, and molder a world with a touch, even he ſuffers himſelf to be crucified in the midſt of theeves, and to die the moſt ignominious death, the death of the Croſs. Learn hence, O man! not to be proud of thine honor, wealth, learning no, nor of thy Piety it ſelf, but lay them all down at the feet of Chriſt, and learn to be meek and lowly in heart,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.29.</note> for ſo was he.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And laſtly we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170533:51"/>hence the Reciprocal love of Parents to their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and of children to their parents.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Virgin-mother did moſt accurately demonſtrate this, when ſhe ſtood near the Croſs with much ſorrow and conſtancy; and how could ſhe chuſe but beſtow on him her choiceſt love, whileſt he was not only her ſon, but alſo the Son of glory? a Son, that according to his Divine generation had a Father with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Mother, and according to his Humane generation had a Mother without a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and therefore may be ſtiled <hi>unigenite,</hi> her only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son: A Son that was qualified with moſt ſpecial endowments, as well of body as ſoul, far excelling both
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170533:52"/>men and Angels. And yet even for this Son, ſhe had no inordinate, no impatient grief; but though his Paſſion was vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent &amp; unparallell'd, yet ſhe beholds him with a holy and a Religious Courage, humbly ſubjecting her ſelf, her ſon and all to the Divine will and diſpoſe of the higheſt: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by giving us this inſtruction, That we look not upon any natural relations, but with a love ſubordinate to the love of God, for he hath told us, <hi>He that loveth ſon or daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter above me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 10.37</note> 
                  <hi>it not worthy of me.</hi> And that whenſoever he calls us to part with them we muſt not unmeaſurably grieve for them, but chearfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign even our deareſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts to that God that hath given them unto us.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:170533:52"/>
               <p n="2">2. Neither was there a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual retribution of love want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on our Saviour his part towards his parent, when not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he was then in the midſt of moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting torments, he forgot not to recommend her to the care of his boſome friend and deareſt Diſciple.</p>
               <p>It is a ſaying among the Heathens, <hi>Diis, Parentibus, &amp; Magiſtris nunquam red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur aequivalens,</hi> The Gods, Parents, and Teachers are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſufficiently gratified. I need not inlarge my ſelf upon this point, even nature it ſelf dictates unto us what love, reſpect, obedience and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is owing to thoſe that begate us, and did for us when we could do nothing for our ſelves. They are
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170533:53"/>therefore to be recompenſed by performing theſe duties to them,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.1 Heb. 12.9</note>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. To obey them in all things in the Lord.</item>
                     <item>2 To bear their corrections with ſubmiſſion.</item>
                     <item>3. To reverence them,<note place="margin">Mal. 1.9</note> in giving them all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſubmiſſion, and fearing to offend them.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5 16.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. To che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and maintain them in time of need.</item>
                  </list> This the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle clearly teacheth, If any faithful man or woman have widows (that is, to their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers or aunts) let them mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter unto them, and let not the Church (that is, other Chriſtians) be charged.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170533:53"/>
                  <p n="1">1. O <hi>Moſt glorious God and gracious Father, that ſenteſt thy Son in no ſort to aſſume the ſhape of Angels, but the nature of a woman, the ſeed of</hi> Abraham; <hi>and didſt glorifie that ſubſtance with the bright robe of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, and place it at thy right hand: We hope and pray that every one of us may have a portion in that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Make us partakers of his Divine nature, as he was of our Humane; make us free from ſin, as he was, holy, as he was holy, and in the end glorifie both our ſouls and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170533:54"/>(with his) in thy heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>O thou Saviour of the world, that wert pleaſed on thy Croſs to caſt an affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate thought on thy dear Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and (amidſt all thy ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows) to chuſe her a Guardian, to have her in his cares; teach us never to forget thoſe duties we owe them that are (under thee) the makers and preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of our lives. Give us grace to love, ſerve, obey and cheriſh them, that ſo we may be as children of their love, ſo heirs of their bleſſing, the bleſſing which thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to loving and obedient children.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>And we beſeech thee (Lord) to teach all parents by her example (who loved thee to the laſt) to be conſtant in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170533:54"/>their affection and care of their children, and to bring them up in thy fear. Let them know that thou art the Father of their ſpirits, they but of their bodies;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 12.9</note> 
                     <hi>let them then put all confidence in thee for them as their beſt Father, and make their daily ſupplications to thee for all goodneſs to them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Thou that didſt favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably look at thy dear Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and adopt him of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, thy mothers ſon; we pray, that the light of thy countenance may ſhine on all us that profeſſe thy Name, make us who are by nature, the children of wrath, by thy grace, inheritors of heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Teach us, with</hi> Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen, <hi>to repent, with the wife of</hi> Cleophas <hi>to proceed in all good and pious works,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170533:55"/>and with the Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>to attain to a good meaſure of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Let us be aſhamed that the weaker Sex ſhould excel us, in the acts of pietie, or religion, yet powre forth thy grace upon all Sexes and all degrees of people, that they may all know, and ſerve thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chiſt whom thou haſt ſent,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 17</note> 
                     <hi>for that is eternal life</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:170533:55"/>
               <head>The Fourth Word.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>MATTH. 27.46.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E have Expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded formerly the three firſt Words which our Saviour ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered on the Croſs about the ſixth hour. We will proceed in the following part of this Treatiſe to unfold four other Words which he ſpake after the Eclipſe and ſilence of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170533:56"/>three hours. But it ſeems very material to declare firſt what that darkneſſe was, and from whence and to what end it was cauſed: Our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt ſaies,<note place="margin">Ver. 45</note> 
                  <hi>From the ſixth hour was there darkneſs over all the earth unto the ninth hour, and then he cryed with a loud voice, ELI, ELI, LAMASABACH THA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NI,</hi> i. <hi>My God, my God, &amp;c.</hi> And that this darkneſs was produced by the defect of the Sun, is elſewhere expreſly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.45</note> 
                  <hi>And the Sun was dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here are ſome difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be ſolved;
<list>
                     <item>1. For the Sun was wont to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in the new Moon, when betwixt the Sun and the earth, there was an interpoſition of the Moon,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170533:56"/>which at the death of Chriſt could not happen, whileſt the Moon was not joyned with the Sun, which is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in the new Moon, but was oppoſite to the Sun, and in its fulneſſe, for then was the Paſſeover of the Jewes, which according to the Law began the fourt eenth day of the firſt month:</item>
                     <item>2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if the Moon was joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the Sun at the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Lord that darkneſs could not continue for three houres; for the eclipſe of the Sun cannot laſt long, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if it be a plenarie Eclipſe, and abſcond the whole Sun; for the Moon moves ſwifter then the Sun according to its proper motion, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this it could not ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow the whole Sun, unleſs
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170533:57"/>it were for a very ſhort Space, for beginning to recede, forthwith it leaves the Sun free, that it might illuminate the earth with its accuſtomed fulgour, as you might obſerve by the laſt greateſt Eclipſe that happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our Horrizon in the year 16.</item>
                  </list> And laſtly there could never be an Univerſal darkeneſs occaſioned through any conjunction of the Sun with the Moon; for the Moon according to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all Aſtronomers is leſſe then the Sun, or the earth, and therefore cannot by the interpoſition of its bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſo mantle the Sun, that the whole earth ſhould be darkned.</p>
               <p>But if ſome do object, That the evangeliſts meant
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170533:57"/>this darkneſs to extend to the whole land of <hi>Paleſtina</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and not abſolutely to the univerſall earth: That opinion might be eaſily refel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, through the teſtimonie of <hi>Dionyſius Arecpagita,</hi> who in his Epiſtle to <hi>Polycar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> witneſſeth himſelf to have ſeen that defection of the Sun, and that horrible darkneſſe in the City of <hi>Heliopolis</hi> which is in <hi>Aegypt.</hi> And <hi>Phl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gon,</hi> a Greek Hiſtorian, and an Heathen, doth remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this Eclipſe, in theſe words, <hi>Quarto anno ducen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſimae ſecundae Olympiadis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2</note> 
                  <hi>magna &amp; excellent inter om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes quae antea acciderant, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio Solis eſt facta, dies ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſexta ita in tenebroſam noctem verſus eſt, ut ſtellae in caeto viſae ſunt.</hi> Among
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170533:58"/>thoſe great and famous things which fell out in the Annalls of the <hi>Olympiads,</hi> there was ſuch an Ecclipſe of the Sun, that the day about the ſixth hour was turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to darknight, that the Stars were ſeen, And this Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian writ not in <hi>Judea.</hi> Of this Author look <hi>Origen</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Celſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euſ. Chron ad annun <hi>Chriſt. 30.3.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his Chronicle, the ſame is teſtified by <hi>Lucian Martyr,</hi> ſaying, * ſearch the Annalls, and you ſhall find that in the times of <hi>Pilate</hi> the Sun be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fled, the day was inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with darkneſs; theſe words of <hi>Lucian</hi> are quoted by <hi>Ruſſiarus,</hi> in his tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Eccleſiaſticall Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Euſebius</hi> into La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin <hi>Tertullian</hi> alſo in his Apolegetick, and <hi>Oſorius</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:170533:58"/>in his Hiſtory, with others,<note place="margin">lib. 7. c. 4</note> do ſpeak not only of <hi>Judea,</hi> but of other parts of the world.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, we may conclude, that though the Eclipſe when it is natural, is wont to happen in the new Moon, and not in the ful, but that at the death of Chriſt was ſingular and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious, and cauſed only by him, who made Sun, Moon and earth: it proceeded not from any natural cauſes, but from the hand of an omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent God; who, as he was able to bring the Moon after an inſolite manner from the Eaſt by a moſt ſwift courſe to the Sun, and after three houres be reduced to its place again, ſo he could effect that the Moon ſhould (as it were) ſtand unmoved under the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170533:59"/>Sun for that ſpace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that it ſhould not move flower, nor ſwifter then the Sun. And whereas it is ſaid, that this deficiency of the Sun could not be univerſall over the whole world, by reaſon the Moon is leſſer then the earth, and much leſſer then the Sun; it is granted, that what the Moon could not do, the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour of Sun and Moon did ſupply, only by not co-opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the Sun, in its illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration; for without his aid and influence, things Created have no power of themſelves to be more; Neither was this darkneſs occaſioned from ſome extraordinary black and thick miſts, as ſome have imagined; for the Ancients affirm that the ſtars were then ſeen in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170533:59"/>Spheares, whereas thick clouds would not only have obſcurd the Sun, but alſo thoſe orbes of leſſer luſtre, as the Moon and the ſtars.</p>
               <p>Why God would have this darkneſs to be ſo Remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable, divers reaſons are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but two eſpecially: the firſt was to ſignifie the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous excaecation of the Jewes,<note place="margin">Leo <hi>in</hi> Ser. <hi>10.</hi> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> paſſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Dem.</note> which does to this day, and ſhall endure accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the vaticinations of <hi>Eſay,</hi> who ſpeaks thus of the beginning of the Goſpel; <hi>Ariſe, O Jeruſalem, be bright, for thy ſight is come, and the Glory of the Lord is riſen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee; for behold, darkneſs ſhall cover the earth, and groſs darkneſs the people:</hi> the other cauſe was to demonſtrate the greatneſs of the Jewes
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170533:60"/>offence, as <hi>Jerome</hi> teacheth. <q>Heretofore (ſaith he) evil men did perſecute,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jerom</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentar. in Matth.</note> vex, and kill the good, now, God himſelfe deſcending to be cloathed in Humane fleſh, they dare perſecute and Crucifie. Heretofore Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens had diſcords with Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, and from diſcords fell to chidings, from chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to wounds, from wounds at length to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous executions, but now ſervants and ſlaves have riſen againſt the King of Men and Angels, and with an incredible audacity have nayled him to a Croſs;</q> Therefore the whole world did tremble, and the Sun it ſelfe drew back it's beames, and hid its face, as deteſting ſo fowl, ſo facinorous an Act,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170533:60"/>as to put the Lord of Life to death, and the darkneſs then was ſo terrible, that it made a Pagan Philoſopher cry out,<note place="margin">Aut deus naturae pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur, aut mundi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>china diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvitur. <hi>Dion. Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op.</hi>
                  </note> either the God of Nature ſuffers, or the whole World is at an end.</p>
               <p>And this was formerly ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pified in the daye; of <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oh,</hi> when there was a great darkneſs over the land of <hi>Egypt</hi> for three dayes,<note place="margin">Exod. 10.21.</note> which was a ſignification of their ſuperſtitious blindneſs and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God, and the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy and diſobedience to Gods Commandment; And as then <hi>Meſes</hi> brought the Iſraelites from the Egyptian bondage they were in, under <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> ſo the true <hi>Moſes</hi> here, Jeſus Chriſt, brings all that believe in him from the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170533:61"/>bondage of Satan unto ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happineſs.</p>
               <p>Let us now come unto the words themſelves, (<hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 22.1.</note>) and theſe we find to be taken out of the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,</hi> and in them Chriſt complains, in a voice more then ordinary, that he was relinquiſhed of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, at that inſtant.</p>
               <p>For the better clearing of the ſenſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we muſt obſerve, that Chriſts derelictions of the Father, may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood five ſeveral wayes, whereof one only is true and here meant: there were five conjunctions or unions in the Son of God, The firſt is that of Eſſence between the firſt and ſecond Perſon of the Glorious Trinity, and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170533:61"/>that as it is natural and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, ſo it is perpetual and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable; of which Chriſt himſelfe ſpeaks, <hi>I and my Father are one,</hi> and therefore he ſaid, not <hi>My Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 8.16.</note> but <hi>My God, why haſt thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me?</hi> For the Father is not called God of the Son, till after, and by reaſon of the Incarnation. 2. The ſecond is the Conjunction of the Divine and Humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the ſecond Perſon, and this can never be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, for what he once took, he never puts off; And the Apoſtle ſaies, <hi>Chriſt, (that is God and Man) ſuffered for us.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21.</note> The third is the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Grace;<note place="margin">Joh. 1.14.</note> 
                  <hi>For Chriſt was a Man full of Grace and truth,</hi> and this doth and ſhall remain: <hi>The juſt dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170533:62"/>for the unjuſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.18</note> the death of Chriſt had nothing profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us, if there had been a ſeparation of Grace; The fourth is the union of Glory, <hi>for the ſoule of Chriſt ſaw God from its very conception,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 1.14.</note> and according to its ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our part was already truely bleſſed,<note place="margin">Aquin. <hi>3.</hi> p. q. <hi>46.</hi> ar. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> and therefore this conjunction could not be diſſolved, becauſe a ſoule once truely bleſſed is alwayes bleſſed; bleſſedneſſe being the ſumm and compendium of all goodneſs: There re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains a fifth union, which is that of Protection, whereof he ſpeaks: <hi>He that ſent me is with me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 8.29.</note> 
                  <hi>and hath not left me alone.</hi> And this for a ſhort time was ſuſpended, and diſſolved, that the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of a bloody ſacrifice
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170533:62"/>might take place for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of mankind.</p>
               <p>God was able divers wayes to have protected Chriſt, and to have withſtood his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to that prayer of his in the Garden.<note place="margin">Marck. 14.36.</note> 
                  <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all things are poſſible to thee, take away this cup from me, nevertheleſs not what I will, but what thou wilt.</hi> Nay, Chriſt could have defended himſelfe, and commanded Legions of Angels to have guarded his Perſon.<note place="margin">Mat. 26.53.</note> 
                  <hi>No man could take his life from him: but he laid it down himſelf;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 10.18.</note> and he might as well beſtowed on his body the gift of impaſſibility, as that of incorruption: But it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Father, it pleaſed the Son, it pleaſed the Holy Ghoſt to permit the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170533:63"/>decree, that humane cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty ſhould prevail againſt him then; he told his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betrayers the hour was come,<note place="margin">Mark. 14.41.</note> in which the Son of man ſhould be delivered into the hands of ſinners, God then ſo left and forſook his Son, that he ſuffered his humanity for that Space to be without any conſolation, &amp; to endure (for our ſins) moſt bitter ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, yea the torments of hell it ſelf.</p>
               <p>And he put himſelf to thoſe unſpeakable ſufferings by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the greatneſſe of mans ſin, which he took on his body to expiate for us, that we being delivered from ſin,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.24</note> ſhould live in righteouſeneſs by whoſe ſtripes we are heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed And as this ſin was infinite as being againſt a perſon of an infinite value, the Lord God, ſo the perſon Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170533:63"/>was to be of an incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible dignitie and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency. And though one drop of his precious blood had been an ampler anſom for all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; yet that his paſſion might be eſteemed by us the more meritorious, and gain more Souls, he ſhed all; becauſe he did undertake for the ſins of the whole world, therefore it pleaſed him to ſuffer a world of torments, when he laboured under that Dereliction of his father.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Learn hence (O man) how infinite and inexpreſible was the love of Chriſt to thee, when he ſuffered with ſo much patience and humilitie ſuch wonderful torments for thy ſins. His ſoul was very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie unto death.<note place="margin">Man 26.3</note> There is no Chriſtian but will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170533:64"/>that our Saviour was ten thouſand times more able to ſuffer then the moſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Martyr that hath ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his Name, and if he were more able to bear whence could it happen that he was preſt with ſuch ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, ſuch heavineſs and ſuch feare? but that he alone ſuffered more then all the martyrs ever ſince righteous <hi>Abel</hi> to this day: this ſhould work an imitation in us to love the bitter cup of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and to reject the cups of Conſolation and Secular delights, to rejoyce in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and to trample on the ſeeming felicities of this world. Doth God viſit our land with Plague, Famine, War or other judgements? O! remember that theſe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170533:64"/>Calamities are but as a drop to that vaſt Ocean of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, the Son Gof od ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for us, and that they are far leſs then our ſins de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; for they are but tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and reach no further then our bodies, but by his ſufferings we are exempted from thoſe miſeries which might juſtly fall on our ſouls and bodies eternally. We then are as priſoners, once condemned for capital crimes, but releaſed again with our lives, and only chaſtized with ſome few ſtripes; have we not then great cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, that we have eſcaped greater judgments?</p>
               <p n="2">2. But though God ſeems for a while to forſake his friends, and leave them in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, and to withdraw his
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:170533:65"/>grace and favour from them; yet his indignation cannot laſt for ever, in the end he will return unto them, and ſhew them the light of his gracious Countenance, and be merciful unto them, if they call upon his glorious name in their diſtreſſes. Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſs ſuffered a great dereliction, his Glory was obſcured, his divinity ſeemed to be hid, the light of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven was ſubſtracted from him, in ſtead of a Diademe, he wore a Crown of thorns, in ſtead of a Scepter a Reed, in ſtead of a ſtatelyretinue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to a King, they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded him the ignominious fellowſhip of two theeves, thus was he dejected, and ſcorned, and expoſed to all imaginable croſſes, but, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170533:65"/>upon his humble expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulation, and prayer to God, the ſence was altered, and a ſpeedy Period put to all theſe calamities, the heavens were unmantled, the light appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, his laſt and worſt enemy (Death) was conquered, his body and ſoul were received in a glorious and triumphant manner into the higheſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, where now he reigns King for evermore.</p>
               <p>And the reaſons why God ſometimes withdrawes his preſence from his People, and deferres their deliverance from afflictions, are to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them throughly, to bring them to an utter denial of themſelves: to learn pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that they might ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg whence their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance and all benefits
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170533:66"/>they enjoy do proceed name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not from themſelves, nor any creature, but from the All-merciful God, and that accordingly they might learn to value and prize his gifts at their deſerved excellency, (for we find this generally verified, that benefits eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obtained, are lightly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded and ſoon forgotten) the children of Iſrael were in captivity about four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and thirty yeares in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, but after they had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the ſalvation of the Lord, they were brought ſafely through the Red ſea,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.</note> by the conduct of <hi>Moſes. David</hi> had a promiſe to be King of Jeruſalem and Judea, but the Lord exerciſed him by many and grievous afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before he came to the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170533:66"/>Crown,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.82.</note> in ſo much that (he ſaies) his eyes failed with waiting upon his God; <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> deſired of God, both of them in their youth, and many years after, for iſſue, but their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt was not granted untill they were old;<note place="margin">Luk. 1.18.</note> the Church Militant for ſome hundreds of yeares after Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, ſeemed to be forſaken and rejected of him, when ſhe was ſo bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by Tyrants, and ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermined by Hereticks, that ſhe was like to be cruſhed and ſtifled in her very cradle, ſhe was tryed ten times in the fire, by ten ſeveral and diſtinct perſecutions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God ſeemed to equal the ten plagues of Egypt, and to lay as much on his people for
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170533:67"/>their probation, as he had laid upon others on their behalfe; More Chriſtian blood effuſed, then in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of the old Law, for ſo we read many a hundred, many a thouſand made Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs in one day, a whole Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, a whole Army deſtroyed at one time for the Goſpels ſake, ſo that as the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites formerly went through the red Sea towards the land of Canaan, theſe through an Ocean of blood paſt to a Kingdom of bliſs. And when the Church had pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and faſted, and ſuffered ſo many years, God in the end hearkned to the voice of her lamentation, took her in his Armes, wiped all teares from her eyes, took away all occaſion of complaint,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170533:67"/>made Kings and Queens to be her Nurſes, and ſo made her Glorious in the eyes of man, acceptable in his, and cheerful in her own ſight; This ought to work a confidence in all Gods af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted ſervants, that he will not quite deſert them; their deliverance will be ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough, if they will wait and depend upon him: a cloud on the skie may for a while ecclipſe the light of heaven, but that will ſoon be diſſipated, and the Sun will appear.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We are further taught by this deſertion of our Saviour to fear to ſin, and to bewail our offences, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſe of his great ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
               <p>What Stoick is ſo void of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170533:68"/>motion, but will be ſenſible to ſee a friend ſuffer for him, what he was himſelf was juſtly guilty of? what Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſo flint-hearted, that will dare commit a ſin, if he does but caſt a ſerious thought on him, who ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo much, not for his own, but our ſins? The Paſſion of Chriſt if rightly conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed may be ſtiled a Schoole, where all Martyrs and Saints are made: who would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of doing too much, of ſuffering too much, of being too much abaſed or deſpiſed, if he do but behold his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour delivered over, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned for him, to ſuch horrible confuſions, ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable torments? (O my God, my wounded God! as long as I ſhall ſee
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170533:68"/>thy wounds,<note place="margin">Nolo vive te fine vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere cum te video vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratum. <hi>Bonaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
                  </note> I will never live without a wound) who will be clothed with purple and coſtly ſilks, and uſed to ſoftneſs and delicacy, and ſee his Redeemer crowned with thorns, and fixed to the Croſs? who will not withhold his hands from violences, and rapines, and ſee Chriſt's armes diſtended on the Croſs? who will not fetter his feet, and hinder them from running after the unbridled deſires of his heart, if he but viewes Chriſt's feet pierced through with nailes? who will not make bitter his tongue, in ſubduing the pleaſures of the taſte, and ſee Chriſt have nothing but gall and vinegar to drink? who will not contemn the ayerie honours of the world, when
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170533:69"/>he beholds him that is able to walk upon the wings of Cherubims; take upon him the forme of a ſervant, and creep among us like a little worm of the Earth? who can delight in any ſinful joy, and behold him ſo ſad, ſo pain'd, ſo dejected? this then is a ſovereign antidote againſt the venome of our ſins, to have our Saviours Image dayly in our hearts, and to reflect our thoughts upon him Crucified in all our actions; When the forty Martyrs were in the frozen lake,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil. or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t.</hi> in 40 mar.</note> thirty nine of them had their mindes wholly bent upon the future Crown, and one of them unhappily thought of nothing but of his puniſhment, All of them remained victorious,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170533:69"/>except this wretched crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who ſoiling the glory of his patience, came out of the poole to dye preſently after in his infidelity. So if our ſuffering Saviour, be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, in all our tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations and temptations; we ſhall be more then Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> but if pleaſure or profit be our objects, we turn our backs to Chriſt, and ſhall have no ſhare in the benefits of his Croſs.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <p>MY God, My God! in what an extaſie is my ſoul, when it contemplates what thou didſt, in thoſe three houres ſilence, when
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170533:70"/>horrour and darkneſs invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the univerſe? when thou wert not in a chair of State, but on thy Croſs, full of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, full of ſufferings!</p>
                  <p>Thou (Lord) who only know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the extremities of thy own Paſſion, teach thy ſervants, how much they owe to thee, and in a religious dejection of themſelves to give thee only the glory of their ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>We know not (Lord) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ſhall more admire the greatneſs of thy love, or the greatneſs of thy Paſſion, both exceed our merits, both ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs our apprehenſions: but ſince thy goodneſs hath thus acted for us, we ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull, if we did not ſpend ſome of thoſe houres which thou haſt given us, in a ſweet
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170533:70"/>recordation of thoſe thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and not only ſo, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print them in our actions.</p>
                  <p>Thou didſt not ſo expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late with thy Father for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſhing of thee, as not knowing the Cauſe; for of what canſt thou be ignorant, who knoweſt all things, and in whom are hid all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of wiſdom and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg? but that thou mighteſt exhort us to ſeek and learn things neceſſary and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for our ſoules.</p>
                  <p>There was no ſeparation between thee and thy God in matter of Eſſence, or grace, or affection, but only in the point of preſent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
                  <p>Thy Father left thee (O Son of God) in that ſad A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gony, that thou mighteſt the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170533:71"/>more gloriouſly triumph; he left thee to ſtruggle with Death, that thou mighteſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Death, and having o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome the ſharpneſs of it, open the Kingdome of heaven to all believers.</p>
                  <p>Thou mighteſt have had a numerous Army of Saints and Angels for thy defence againſt thy enemies, and death it ſelf; (for all Power in heaven and earth was given unto thee O Lord) but thou wert pleaſed to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that Divine decree be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thee and thy Father, and thy Spirit, that thou ſhouldſt firſt ſuffer all theſe things, and then to enter into thy Glory.</p>
                  <p>But tell us we pray thee (Thou Lever of Men) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no did the vehemency of thy ſorrowes in that ſpace,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170533:71"/>ſilence thine heart from thine accuſtomary devotion? for we when we are but toucht with any affliction, can ſcarce lift up a thought to thee, or ſpeak of thy prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
                  <p>But (O our Saviour) it was not ſo with thee; for though thy fleſh was weak, yet thou didſt bear a Spirit prompt to all holy exerciſes. We know that though thy tongue moved not; yet with the mouth of thine heart thou didſt ſend implicit ejacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to thy Father for us; neither didſt thou only pray in heart, but in wounds and blood; And as many wounds as were in thy Sacred body, ſo many ſupplicants there were for us to thy heavenly Father; and as many drops
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170533:72"/>of blood, ſo many tongues petitioning mercy for us.</p>
                  <p>O our God! we are juſtly confounded in the Abyſſe of thy love and mercy to the ſons of men. O were our ſins ſo great that no ſacrifice could at tone thine Anger but the blood of thy Son, thy only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son, in whom alone thou art well pleaſed! O ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant love! O prodigious Mercy!</p>
                  <p>But (Lord) teach us by his example not to caſt cur affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the pleaſures and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of this world, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the cup of affliction whereof he drank in an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing meaſure.</p>
                  <p>Make us fear to ſin for his ſake who ſinn'd not and yet ſo highly ſuffered for our ſins, and when me fall under
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170533:72"/>the rod of thy diſpleaſure for them, correct us not in thy fury, leſt we ſhould be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and brought to nothing.</p>
                  <p>Though thou doſt eclipſe thy ſavours ſometimes from thy dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt ones, yet we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident thou wilt not totally and finally forſake thoſe who do not (ſo) forſake thee.</p>
                  <p>Therefore we pray thee be not farre from us (O God) and though we attribute to thy Juſtice the glory of our deſerved ſufferings, yet let thy mercy have the glory of our deliverance from them, for the Paſſion of thy ſon's ſake. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:170533:73"/>
               <head>The fifth Word.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>JOHN 19.28.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>1 Thirſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the better explanation of This, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to add the precedent and ſubſequent words of the Evangeliſt: <hi>After this, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus knowing that all things were now accompliſhed, that the Scripture might be fulfilled, ſaith, I thirſt; now there was ſet a veſſel full of vinegar, and they filled a
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170533:73"/>ſpunge with vinegar, and put it upon hyſſop and put it to his mouth.</hi> The Lord would have a full Conſummation of all the Propheticall predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his life and death, this only remained according to the Pſalmiſt;<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.21.</note> 
                  <hi>They gave me vinegar to drink;</hi> Our Lord ſaid, <hi>I thirſt.</hi> The Prophet foretold it, becauſe he foreſaw it; the predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or previſion is not the cauſe of a thing to Come, but the thing to come is the ground of either. The emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſo much blood, could not chuſe but provoke an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of thirſt, (as I knew a man grievouſly wounded, who called for nothing but drink) which notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he entertained with a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſilence from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170533:74"/>of his Crucifixion: His fleſh had been long unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with any moyſture; his veines, his tongue, his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and all his Interiours did labour under a miſerable dryneſs, but, O ſad refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment! in ſtead of giving him Cordials, or pleaſant drinks, they offer him that which might either increaſe his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or haſten his diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The ſumm of all is this: As a little before his affixction to the Croſs, <hi>they offered him Wine mingled with Gall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 27.</note> ſo in the laſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of his life, <hi>they brought him Vinegar,</hi> that from the beginning to the end he might have a continued Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, not mixed with any ſolace or refreſhment.</p>
               <p>The new Teſtament is for
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170533:74"/>the moſt part an explanation of the Old, but in this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Lords Thirſt, the words of the Pſalmiſt may be ſtyled a Commentary on theſe words of Chriſt, <hi>I look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ſome to ſorrow with me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 69.</note> 
                  <hi>but there was none, and for Comforters, and I found none, they gave me gall to eat, and vinegar to drink,</hi> And of ſuch the Lord here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, and ſaies, <hi>I thirſt:</hi> Hence learn firſt, O Man!</p>
               <p n="1">1. To poſſeſſe thy ſoul in patience in thy afflictions af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the great example of our Lord and Maſter Chriſt; though in the fourth word there ſhined his humility joyned with his Patience, yet here it appeares in its proper place. <q>This is it which ſetteth a ſeal upon
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170533:75"/>all vertues, even the firſt in the liſt, and laſt in the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. It is the Crowned Pomegranate which hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth among bells in the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt border of the high Prieſts robe of the old Law, all was imperfect without the Crown of Patience;</q> it is the Salt of the Prophet <hi>Eliſaeus,</hi> which purifieth the polluted waters, and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all the bitterneſs of life, it is the School of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. So learned are we, as we have Patience,<note place="margin">Ambroſs in Prov. <hi>19</hi>
                  </note> ſo much do we participate with God, as we can endure by his example, he hath taken a body, to be able to ſuffer, and to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the mirrour and reward of ſufferours. But we muſt diſtinguiſh true Patience
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170533:75"/>from falſe. True patience is that, which commands us to ſuffer the evils of puniſhment, that it may not enforce us to commit the evils of ſin, ſuch was the patience of true Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, who would rather under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the torments of villanous executions, then deny the ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith of Chriſt; and would rather tolerate the loſs of all they had, then adhibit any adoration to falſe Gods, falſe patience is that which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades us to ſuffer all evil things, that we may obey the law of luſt, and to looſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal things, to conſerve the Temporal, ſuch is the patience of the Devils Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, who will eaſily ſuffer hunger, thirſt, cold, heat, the loſs of a good name, (and which is to be admired) of
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:170533:76"/>the kingdom of heaven, that they might augment their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſatisfie carnal concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and aſcend to the ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery mount of honours.</p>
               <p>It is the innate property of true Patience to continue in a good cauſe to the end, till by working it hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed us,<note place="margin">Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 1.1.</note> and made us per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect men; and that is it which the Apoſtle declares in the Encomiums of it: other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues cannot long ſubſiſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, in regard of ſome difficulties which are found in their actuations, which by her aſſiſtance, are conquered with much facility;<note place="margin">Cyprian ſer de patieut.</note> 
                  <q>Charity which is the Queen of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, the ground of peace, the link of unity, &amp; greater then either faith, or hope, or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170533:76"/>take from it Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and it remains deſolate, take from it the ſubſtance of ſuffering, and it hath no root, no ſtrength to perſevere:</q> without this the chaſte man cannot reſiſt uncleanneſs, the juſt cannot be free from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, nor the peaceable, from a deſire of Revenge. The Pſalmiſt ſaies,<note place="margin">Pſal 9.18.</note> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation (or Patience) of the Poor (or humble) ſhall not periſh for ever, but the fruit of it ſhall be perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly verdant; the husband-man loſes not the ſweats of his brow, when he beholds his ſeed flouriſhing in the eare; And the patient ſouldier de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves as great trophies as the greateſt Conquerour, when by the ſweetneſs of his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, he doth, as it were
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170533:77"/>trampled on the victories of his enemies; he that endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to the end ſhall receive a Crown of Glory.<note place="margin">Ja. 1.12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>We need no other Motive to induce us to this Royal vertue, then the King of ſufferings; Chriſt Jeſus thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting on the Croſs, for not to ſpeak of all his afflictions and miſeries, which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued from his cradle to his grave; this his tedious and vehement thirſt is ſufficient to enflame our ſouls with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious patience in all our tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations. But, leaſt we ſhould miſtake the practice of it with (the Romiſh Saint) <hi>Macarius,</hi> who hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing killed a gnat which prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him,<note place="margin">Vitae P. P.</note> (as if he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a great act of impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience) went for the ſpace of
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170533:77"/>ſix moneths, expoſing his naked body to all the flies, gnats, and waſps of the wilderneſs, to be revenged upon himſelf; let's take theſe few directions.
<list>
                     <item>1. To bear a little with our ſelves, and be content with thoſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and callings wherein we are placed: it is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of imprudent perſons to be weary with the preſent and ever gaping for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</item>
                     <item>2. To be full of mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and lenity towards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, bearing with their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities: ſome hath more diſturbances then the winding <hi>Eruipus</hi> hath waves, but what unreaſonableneſs is it, that a man full of rebellions againſt God, ſhould deſire that men and beaſts ſerve him, according to all his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</item>
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:170533:78"/>
                     <item>3.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16, 10, 11.</note> To ſuffer calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſlanderous words, as <hi>David</hi> did thoſe of Shemei.</item>
                     <item>4. To endure all humane accidents, as ſickneſſes, loſs of goods, hunger and thirſt, impriſonments, baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, death of friends and neer Relations, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever hath ſadneſs and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in nature, ever acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that they are but ſcourges for our ſins (which deſerves greater) and that none of them happen with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the permiſſion of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine power, to which we muſt all ſubmit, that ſo, the incenſed God, being appeaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, may vouchſafe us his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictions, and enboſom us as his ſons, by his paternal fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But beſides this corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170533:78"/>thirſt, the Lord ſeems to me to intend a ſpiritual one, and to have ſpoken theſe words in the ſame ſenſe, as thoſe to the women of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, Give me to drink.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, unlocking the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of his ſpeech, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes this, <hi>if thou kneweſt the gift of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 4.7, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>and who it is that ſaith to thee, give me to drink, thou wouldſt have asked of him, and he will give thee the water of life.</hi> When I behold Chriſt upon the Croſs as it were upon the high Mount, looking on ſo many millions, languiſhing through the inflamations of their ſins, I behold the ſame Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerating their ſad conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſaying, though I truly thirſt for the exhauſted and dried humour of my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170533:79"/>yet I more thirſt and covet that man at length may by faith acknoledg me to be the true fountain of that living water, and that they may come to me and drink, and ſo they ſhall not thirſt eternally.</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe are the words of the Prophet. <hi>Ho, Everyone that thirſteth come to the waters,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 55.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and he that hath no money, come buy and eat; come I ſay, buy wine and milk without money, without price.</hi> That you may conceive they are not ſcrew'd to too high a value, he invites you with a ſecond call; theſe waters are ſaid to be bought, becauſe they are not to be had without ſome labour and induſtry, but they are had without any commutation,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170533:79"/>becauſe they are given freely, neither can there be any price found to parallel the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their worth; what he firſt called Water, he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards cals Wine and Milk, thereby to diſplay unto us the excellency and perfection of the gift; what is called Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is divine Wiſdom, which quencheth the flames &amp; luſts of Concupiſcence; by Wine is meant that celeſtial cale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction which doth warm and brisk the ſoul, making it to covet things heavenly and ſublime; and it is called Milk, becauſe it ſweetly nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed the Infants in Chriſt with eternal food.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Some thirſt, with a moſt flaming deſire, and inſatiable greedineſs after the tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this world, (which
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170533:80"/>the vulgar call bleſſings) as honours, wealth, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, but our deſires muſt mount higher, and have theſe three Objects, the glory of God, the honour of Chriſt, and the ſalvation of our ſouls, that theſe were the vehement deſires of Chriſt, all his works, all his preachings, all his ſufferings, and all his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles do voice and ſpeak it. The Prophet cries out. <hi>As the hart brayeth for the rivers of water,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo panteth my Soul, after thee, O God. My Soul thirſteth for God, even for the living God, when ſhall I come and appear before the preſence of God?</hi> Behold, how this King, who was clad with the rags of mortality, and ſoyled with the vileneſs of carnal vanities, thirſts after Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:170533:80"/>and ſervice here, and to enjoy the beatifical viſion of him hereafter:<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Pauls</hi> zeal towards Gods Glory, was ſuch, that he would redeem the rejection of the Jews, with his own damnation; to teſtifie his great deſire for their Salvation, he wiſht to be anathematized from Chriſt. He had rather be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the heavenly Glory then that Chriſt ſhould be deprived of ſo great a fault of his paſſion, which would have appeared in the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſo many thouſand Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites. Now, if Chriſt, if <hi>Paul</hi> and others ſo eagerly thirſted for our ſalvation, why do we our ſelves neglect it? Why do we ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently covet theſe temporals, which are weightleſs and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaneous,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170533:81"/>and not place our whole effections on that happineſs, which is glorious and eternal? The reaſon peradventure is, becauſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Glory is not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paled within the dominion of ſenſe: we have not that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal experiment of it, as of corporal felicity, which makes us earneſtly covet this, ſlightly deſire the other; and <hi>therefore the natural man (who ſees not beyond the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſenſe) perceiveth not the things of the Spirit of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14</note> 
                  <hi>for they are fooliſhneſs to him. But he that is ſpiritual diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth all things.</hi> There muſt be a ſpiritual wiſdome in us, before we can long for the things above, and this is not to be found in the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> of the world, but in
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170533:81"/>the moſt Divine Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of Gods Spirit,<note place="margin">Jam. 1.5.</note> the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and fountain of all true knowledg, who gives libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to all, and reproacheth none. Thither only we muſt make our humble ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes for this holy Gemme, and not deſiſt in our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, untill we have by our teares, and cryes, undeaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the eares of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> ANd now, O God, of all pity and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, we are confounded to conſider thy great goodneſs, in ſuffering that extremity of thirſt, and pain, for us on the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170533:82"/>Croſs; enable us to bear pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently all afflictions, Corporal or ſpiritual, and to ſubmit our wills to thine, in ſickneſs as in health, in woe as in wealth, in death as in life.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Make us to thirſt after the Kingdom of heaven and its righteouſneſs; teach us to prize the ſalvation of our ſoules above all earthly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, for they are ſpiritual, immortal, and precious, theſe but tranſitory, and ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, if we ſeek thee in the firſt place, (who art All in All) no bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſings whether cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, ſpirituall, or eternal can be wanting to us, for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good and perfect gift pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from thee above,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lights.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:170533:82"/>
               <head>The ſixth Word.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>JOHN 19.30.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS implies no more in ſound conſtruction, then that the wonderful work of the Paſſion is now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummated and completed; for the Father enjoyned the Son, two weighty offices or works, one of preaching the Goſpel, the other of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for man; of the firſt the
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170533:83"/>Lord formerly ſaid, <hi>That he had finiſhed the work which he gave him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 17.5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and manifeſted his name unto men.</hi> The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther injunction is intimated in theſe words, <hi>O my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if this Cup may not paſs away from me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 26 42.</note> 
                  <hi>except I drink it, thy will be done.</hi> Now he had fully exhauſted that bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cup of his Paſſion, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing remained but his diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and ſo with an incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning head he gave up the Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>But being neither our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, nor S. <hi>John</hi> explained what was Finiſhed, occaſion is given us to make ſuch my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall applications of the Word, as may be fruitfull to our ſouls;<note place="margin">Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. <hi>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cum.</hi>
                  </note> One of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers affirmes, That in this place is meant, an impletion
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170533:83"/>of the Prophecies foretold of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Eſay 7. Mick. 2.</note> and that all thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions were true; as his conception of a Virgin, his Nativity in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 23.</note> the apparatition of a new Starr,<note place="margin">Pſal. 71.</note> the Adoration of Kings, the Preaching of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Iſay 61.</note> His Miracles, his riding upon an aſs,<note place="margin">Eſay 35. Pſal. 21.68 Eſa. 53. Jer. 11. Zach. 12.</note> And his whole Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is deſcribed by parts, by <hi>David</hi> in his Pſalmes, <hi>Eſay, Jeremy, Zachary,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and this the Lord himſelf being to paſs to his ſufferings, ſpake, <hi>Behold,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luck. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>we go up to Jeruſalem, and all things that are written by the Prophets concerning the Son of Man, ſhall be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> which is alſo here averred, that their Teſtimonies might he verrified, and received as
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170533:84"/>the dictates of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another of the Fathers underſtands here,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> that the power which was permitted to Men and Angels againſt Chriſt, was now conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at his Death; and to this effect he ſpeaks to the Chief Prieſts and Captains of the Temple, and the elders that were with him, <hi>this is your hour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 22.53.</note> 
                  <hi>and the power of darkneſs;</hi> now his laborious peregrination, now the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of his mortal life ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which he hungred and thirſted, and was weary, and obnoxious to injuries, wounds, and to death it ſelfe, is fully ended and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Another makes this Conſtruction, Now the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170533:84"/>Sacrifice was Conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that, in which all the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of the old Law, as it were, types and ſhadowes did reſt, and into which they run, as Rivolets into the main Ocean: or as the ſtars, when the Sun appeares with his glorious rayes, ſee no ſtars at all, ſo thoſe typical oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons all vaniſhed, at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of this Son of Glory, when he was to be immolated. Concerning theſe prefigura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions one ſpeaks thus. <q>Lord, thou haſt attracted all things to thy ſelfe;<note place="margin">Leo Serm. <hi>8.</hi> de poſſion dom.</note> for the vaile of the Temple being rent, the holy things of the moſt holy departed from the unworthy Prieſts, that the figure might be turned into the truth, Prophecy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to manifeſtation, and the
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:170533:85"/>law into the Goſpel, (and a little after) the variety of carnal ſacrifices now cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the oblation of thy body, and blood have made one perfect and entire ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice:</q> For in this Sacrifice the Prieſt is God-man, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Hypoſtatical union. <hi>Thou art a Prieſt for ever after the order of Melchizedeck;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 109.4</note> The Altar was the Croſs, which, by how much the more baſe it was before, by ſo much the more illuſtrious and noble it was made after Chriſts death, the Sacrifice was the Lamb of God, innocent, and immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, of whom the Prophet ſaid, <hi>That he was brought as a ſheep to the ſlaughter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 53.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and as a ſheep before the ſhear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is dumb, ſo he openeth not
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:170533:85"/>his mouth.</hi> The fire of the Holocauſt was his immenſe charity,<note place="margin">Cant. 1.8</note> which did ſo flame in his breſt, that the floods of perſecutions could not extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it; the fruit of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice was the redemption of Mankind, the expiation of the ſins of all the ſons of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> for,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.29.</note> 
                  <hi>behold he is the Lamb of God that taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſins of the world:</hi> But here is the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſacrifices under the Law, and this of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, there it was the Office of the Prieſt to kill, and to prepare the Sacrifice, but here Chriſt was both Prieſt and Sacrifice, not that he layd violent hands on himſelf, but becauſe he willingly yielded to the ſlaughter, for Gods glory and the propitiation of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170533:86"/>our ſins, their reconciliation was obtained by the blood of beaſts,<note place="margin">Col. 1.20.</note> here peace is made through the ſacred blood of Chriſt Jeſus, not his, as he claimes all the beaſts of the forreſt, all the cattell upon a thouſand hills,<note place="margin">Pſa. 50.10.</note> and all the foules of the Mountains to be his; not his, as he is Lord and proprietary of all by Creation, ſo all blood in his; no, nor his, as the blood of all the Martyrs was his, (which is a neer relation and Conſanguinity) but his ſo, as it was the blood of his Croſs, the precious blood of his body, the ſeat of his ſoul, the matter of his Spirits, and the knot of his dear life.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We may further under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand in this place, that at the death of Chriſt a great bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170533:86"/>was finiſhed between him and the Prince of this world; of which he intimates in thoſe words: <hi>Now is the judgement of this world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jo. 12.31.</note> 
                  <hi>now ſhall the Prince of it be caſt out:</hi> but this battell was judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, not military, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters were in litigations, not armes, for the devill did ſtrive with the Son of God, about the poſſeſſion of the world, that is, of humane kind, the Devill had for a long time uſurped a domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over man, becauſe he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered the firſt man, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved him, and his whole poſterity, and therefore he is ſtiled the Principalities and Powers of the world,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.12.</note> and the Prince of darkneſs; Neither was he only ſo called,<note place="margin">Pſal. 96.5.</note> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo termed the Gods of the
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:170533:87"/>heathen, for he was publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adored with ſacrifices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, as their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God: but on the other part, Chriſt, as the true and lawfull heire of the univerſe, claimed to himſelfe the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities of the world, ſo that at length the battell was decided on the Croſs, and ſentence was given in favour of our Saviour, where he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Trophees of an abſolute Conqueſt, for there he gave a plenary ſatisfaction to the Divine Juſtice for the tranſgreſſions of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, for there is returned a greater obedience from the Son to the Father, then was the inobedience of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to the Lord; the Son of God was more humbled even to death for the honour of
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170533:87"/>the father, then man was lifted to pride, to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God; ſo God was reconciled to man through the merits of his Son, when he reſcued him from the clawes of the Devil,<note place="margin">Col. 1.</note> and tranſlated him into the Kingdom of his beloved ſon.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And laſtly, theſe words may rightly be applyed to the building of Chriſt<hi>'s</hi> Church, which was not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and finiſhed until his paſſion, though inchoated in his Baptiſme. Thus <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> in his third book againſt Hereſies, and that learned and holy <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>haere.</hi> 78.</note> in his laſt book of the City of God affirm and teach,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 22. <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>Eve</hi> being built and founded on the rib of <hi>Adam,</hi> he being
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170533:88"/>a ſleep, was a type of the Church, which was raiſed from Chriſts ſide, when he began to ſleep through the heavineſs of death, and ſo the Scriptures do notifie, (not without a myſtery) <hi>Eve</hi> to have been built, not formed. And that the Church began to be edified from the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of Chriſt, the ſaid Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proves out of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt. His dominion ſhall be from ſea to ſea,<note place="margin">Pſal. 71.8.</note> and from the river to the ends of the world; for the Kingdome of Chriſt which is the Church, began to be built from the water of his Baptiſme, in which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Baptiſme of <hi>John,</hi> conſecrated the waters, and inſtituted his own, which is the gate of the Church, and this he was made manifeſt
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170533:88"/>through that voice of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heard from heaven; this <hi>is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed hear him;</hi> from that time the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to preach and to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregate Diſciples, who were the firſt that came to the Church, and although there was made an aperſion of Chriſt's ſide after death, from whence iſſued forth water and blood, which ſignified thoſe two principal Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Church, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and the Lords Supper, yet all ordinances had their full qualifications from his meritorious paſſion; ſo that the flowing of water and blood from his ſide, was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a declaration of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, rather then an inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution moſt rightly, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:170533:89"/>it is ſaid, that the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Church was then conſummated; when he ſaid, It is finiſhed, for there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained nothing then but a diſſolution, which ſpeedily following, the price of a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed redemption for man was compleated.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Learn hence, O man, that as thou art certain thoſe things by their events to have been true, which the holy Prophets predicted, ſo thou ought'ſt to be fully aſſured, that thoſe future things which are foretold by the ſame Prophets, ſhall come to paſs, though not as yet fulfilled, for they ſpake not from hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane fancies, but from an inſpiring Spirit of God, which is ever infallible. <q>
                     <hi>Sicut uſque ad hodiernam diem,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:170533:89"/>omnia evenerunt;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aug.</hi> in Pſal. 76.</note> 
                     <hi>ſic et quae reſtant, eventura ſunt,</hi> &amp;c. Even as to this day all things have rightly follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo the things which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main will undoubtedly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. Let us fear then the day of judgment; the Lord is coming, he that came once in poverty, will next come in Glory.</q> And that there be no haeſitation in our ſaith, we have ſtronger ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments on our ſides then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our <hi>Anceſtors</hi> had: they who preceded the times of Chriſt, without any perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, or external impleti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were tyed to believe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things; we, who have had an experimental knowledg of diverſe things already accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, ſhould be induced to credit the reſt with the more
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:170533:90"/>facility: who lived in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> did here that the general deluge was to come, and it was demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto them, not only by his preaching, but alſo by his building of an Ark, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they would not believe becauſe they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen ſuch a deluge, and therefore a divine fury fell ſuddenly on them, now we who know, that to be impleted which the Prophet foretold, may eaſily believe that he, at whoſe beck are all the elements, may as well deſtroy the world by fire, the ſecond time, as he hath done firſt, by water: And we that find it verified, that Chriſt raiſed many from death, and his own body from the grave, may be fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:170533:90"/>that by virtue of his Reſurrection our ſoules and bodies alſo ſhall be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a ſtate of glory and immortality in the world to come.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Obſerve that though the journey of our Saviours peregrination here was labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and ſharp above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, yet it received an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable compenſation, it ended in triumph and Glory; it laſted thirty three years, but what was the labour of thoſe years in compariſon of Eternal happineſs? he was humbled and made a ſcorn of men, and an abject of the people, for a ſhort time, but God hath highly exalted him,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.9, 10.</note> and given him a name above every name, that at the name of Jeſus every knee
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170533:91"/>ſhould bow, of things in heaven, things in earth, and things under the earth: But his adverſaries exulted to the period of his Paſſion; <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> rejoyced till the inſtant of his ſufferings, becauſe he had preſerved his friendſhip with <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and was then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to King <hi>Herod,</hi> but now he and the perfidious Jewes juſtly ſuffer in hell-flames for their ſacrilegious impieties. Here then the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and patient men, may ſee how good, how propitious a thing it is; to take up the Croſs in this life, and to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt, their afflictions are but light and tranſcient, and not worthy to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the glory which ſhall be revealed to them; for when they dye, they paſs
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:170533:91"/>from a vaile of ſorrowes to a Paradiſe of joyes,<note place="margin">Rev. 7.16.</note> where all teares ſhall be wiped from their eyes: but with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly it is not ſo, the end of their miſeries (if they have any) in this world, is but an entrance and beginning of greater in the other, where is endleſs weeping, and wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Another benefit may be reaped from the third ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of the words; for if we mean that the Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the chiefeſt Prieſt is now finiſhed on the Croſs, it followes, that all his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in imitation of their Maſter, according to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral talents ſhould offer like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Sacrifices to their God; in this ſence all Chriſtians are Prieſts to offer Sacrifices,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.9.</note>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:170533:92"/>not ſuch as were in the old Teſtament,<note place="margin">i <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9</note> but Spirituall Prieſts, to offer myſtical ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, which may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented from all men, as praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and prayers, and other ſervices of piety; the ſame is moſt occurately taught us in the Epiſtle to the Romans,<note place="margin">Heb. i3.i5, 16.</note> in reſemblance of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the ancient Law;<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1</note> for there was in them.
<list>
                     <item>1. The hallowed to God, which to convert to profane uſe, was held a nafarious Crime.</item>
                     <item>2. It was to be a thing living, as a ſheep, or goate, or the like.</item>
                     <item>3. It was to be holy, that is, clean; for there were among the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> animals clean and unclean,</item>
                     <item>4. And then the thing hallowed to God, was to be burn't, that it might ſend forth an odour
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:170533:92"/>of ſweetneſs: The like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties muſt be found in our ſpiritual Sacrifices,
<list>
                           <item>1. Our bodies ought to be hallowed to God, that we may uſe them to his honour, not as our own, but his, to whom they are conſecrated by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and who hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed them by his blood.</item>
                           <item>2. They ought to be living ſacrifices, enlivened with the life of Grace, and of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit: for whoſoever are dead by ſin, are not fit Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctimes for God, but for the devils; our God, who is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes living, and the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fountain of life, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors the ſtinking oblations of dead carkaſſes, who are profitable for nothing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs for dogs and fowles of the Aire. We muſt then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balm
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:170533:93"/>and preſerve the life of the ſoul, with our beſt and moſt religious actions, that we may give a reaſonable ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to our God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. We muſt be holy and clean; for none ſhall aſcend into the hill of the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.3, 4</note> or ſtand in his holy place, but he that hath clean hands, and a pure heart, who hath not lift up his ſoul unto vanity, nor ſworn deceitfully.</item>
                           <item>4. And then we muſt be well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and ſend up a ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to our God, to that purpoſe in the old Law, they uſed to kill and burn the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifie; and this is rightly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the ſpiritual Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, when carnal concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence is truly mortified, and burn't with the coales of charity; nothing can ſooner
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:170533:93"/>or more effectually deſtroy it, then a ſincere love to God, for he is Lord and King of all the affections of the heart, and rules them all, whether Fear, Hope, Deſire, Hatred, Anger, or any other perturbation of the ſoul; and love doth not yeild but to a greater, ſo that when divine love doth poſſeſs, and bear dominion over the inmoſt corners of the heart; then carnal concupiſcence gives place, and being mortified, it vaniſheth to nothing.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list> Thence flaming deſires, and moſt pure prayers aſcend to heaven, like aromatical per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes of precious ſpices: this then is that perfect and acceptable ſacrifice which God requires; and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:170533:94"/>here exhorts with a moſt perſuaſive argument. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you by the mercies of God, that you preſent your bodies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that is, as if he had ſaid, by him, that created you ſomething, when you were nothing: By him that made you his ſervants, and needed not your ſervice, and when your merits were una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileable, bleſt you with his own; by him that made you to his own ſimilitude, and by this, capable of his love and knowledg; by him that made you his adoptive ſons, and co-heirs with his unige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit; by him that made you members of his body, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was the head; by him that offered himſelf a full and propitiatory ſacrifice on the
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:170533:94"/>Croſs, to redeem you from ſervitude, and waſh you from all ſpots and wrinkles; by him, I beſeech you, to give to God in ſtead of dead beaſts, lively ſacrifice; in ſtead of their blood, which was but a ſhadow, and pleaſed not God of it ſelf, the accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſacrifice of the ſpiritual man, framed by faith, to godlineſs and charity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And then we are here further taught, that we ſhall be crowned with Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, and Diademes of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happineſs if we fight cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageouſly under the banner of Chriſt, againſt our ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al enemies, and never deſiſt until we have obtained the Victory. Chriſt gave not over until all was finiſhed: If God had given over at his
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:170533:95"/>ſecond dayes work, we had had no ſin, no ſeaſons; if at the fifth, we had no being; if at the ſixth, no ſabbath, but by proceeding to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, we are all, we have all; So Chriſt, if he had ſtayd at his Circumciſion, or his Agony, or his ſcourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, our redemption had been imperfect, but by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing to his crowning and his nayling, and the piercing of his ſide on the Croſs, all was completed that was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for mans ſalvation.<note place="margin">2 King. 5.24</note> 
                  <hi>Naaman</hi> could not be cured of his leproſie, but by waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Jordan</hi> ſeven times, leſs could not do it; it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for a man to begin, or do ſome few acts of piety or religion, unleſs he make; a conſtant progreſs
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:170533:95"/>therein. Are the Angels weary of looking on that face of God, which they looked upon yeſterday? or are the Saints weary of ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Allelujah, which they ſung to Gods glory yeſterday? Is not that ſong which is their morning and evening ſacrifice; and which ſhall be their ſong world without end, called ſtill, A new ſong? Oh! then ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be weary, never give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver performing thy duties to that God that never ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to bleſs thee; for he (and he only) that continues un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end, ſhall receive a Crown of life.</p>
               <p>In vain did the perfidious Jews cry, if he be King of Iſrael, let him come down from the Croſs, and we will
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:170533:96"/>believe in him; Nay, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe he was ſo, he would not deſert his place; for by his perſeverance, his intereſt to the Kingdome was confirmed, and the work of redemption was conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſuch a glorious manner, that nothing could be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, to the greatneſs of its merit, or to enduce us to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſo noble a preſident; to proceed in thoſe actions, that are pleaſant and ſuitable to our temper is facil, and not praiſe worthy; but to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in laborious Agonies and ſorrows, and in ſuch things as are againſt the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of our own natural and carnal affections is indeed difficult, but very laudable. Chriſt was ſo enamoured with his divine Father, and
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:170533:96"/>long'd ſo earneſtly for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of man, that all intervening Croſſes ſeemed Cordials to him, and all pains, pleaſures: After his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample we find that <hi>Paul</hi> enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merating his own ſufferings with thoſe of his Co-Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles breaks thus forth; who is able to ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt?<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> ſhall tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation or diſtreſs? ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, perſecution, or famine, or nakedneſs, or peril, or ſword? As it is written, for thy ſake we are killed, all the day long, we are counted as ſheep for the ſlaughter, Nay; in all theſe things we are more then conquerours, through him that loved us. From theſe holy preſidents we may learn how to maſter our afflictions, and to ſweeten
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:170533:97"/>our perſecutions, and to deem them as the embrioes of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life: We may bear them with all ſpiritual joy, if we look not on them, but on him, that impoſed them on us, who without doubt was the Father Almighty, without whoſe Providence, not a hair can fall from our heads, and therefore let us with <hi>Moſes</hi> eſteem his rebukes greater riches then the treaſures of <hi>Egypt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. ii. 26.</note> having reſpect unto the recompence of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="185" facs="tcp:170533:97"/>
                  <p n="1">1. ANd now, (O Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the world!) how great a compaſs wentſt thou in this act of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, before thou didſt bring it to this happy Period, from thy ſwathing to thy ſhrowding, from thy cold lying in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to thy cold dying upon the Croſs, what didſt thou do and ſuffer? Nay, what didſt thou not do and ſuffer for us.</p>
                  <p>The work of our Creation was great, but this far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. That was done with a Fiat, with the breath of thy mouth, thou ſpeakeſt the Word and all was done; here was
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:170533:98"/>a miraculous conjunction of God and man in one perſon, maid and mother in another, when it was but begun, thy omnipotencie indeed appeared in the firſt, but thy mercy and juſtice in the latter; ſuch a work didſt thou finiſh here, that neither Man, nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or thy deity alone could well accompliſh.</p>
                  <p>Oh! Thou that didſt ſo much for us, teach us to do ſomewhat for thee. Thou that madeſt thy ſelf a perfect victime for our ſins, grant that we may ſacrifice our ſins, and mortifie all carnal concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcences, that ſo our ſouls and bodies may be offerings of a ſweet ſmelling Saviour in thy Noſtrils.</p>
                  <p>Thou that didſt conquer the Prince of this world, and
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:170533:98"/>all the enemies upon the Croſs, aſſiſt us againſt the conflicts and temptations of our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual adverſaries; ſave us from the roaring Lyon, that he may never prevail; O thou, that art the Lion of the tribe of <hi>Judah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But becauſe we are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of our ſelves, what to do aright,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.6.</note> we pray thee guide us with thy Spirit; thou,<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.21.</note> who workeſt all in all, work thy work in us, and bring to paſs thy act, thy ſtrange act, whatever it be.</p>
                  <p>Let us perform what thou requireſt of us, and that is, let us do juſtly, ſhew mercy, and walk humbly with thee,<note place="margin">Mic. 6.8.</note> and walk humbly with thee, our God.</p>
                  <p>Preſerve thy Church, that iſſued from thy ſide on thy Croſs; thou art her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:170533:99"/>(O Chriſt) ſave thy ſpouſe, thou art her head, ſave thy body; protect her, as thine from infidels, hereticks and ſchiſmaticks; from bad men and Devils, from all errours and dangers.</p>
                  <p>Make her (unto thy ſelf) glorious, without ſpot or wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle; holy and without ſin;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.7.</note> And though (like thee) ſhee ſorrows and ſuffers often, while militant here; yet make her triumphant (with thee) in the world to come.</p>
                  <p>Let every member of her, profeſs thy name to the end with courage, and conſtancy, after thy glorious Examples: let us not be carried away from our duties to thee, with the vanities of the world, or the enticements of the fleſh, or the ſuggeſtions of Satan.</p>
                  <pb n="189" facs="tcp:170533:99"/>
                  <p>O thou that art immutable, without ſhadow of change Yeſterday, to day and the ſame for ever; fix our fickle thoughts on thy fear, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh thy holy Spirit within us, that we may alwayes praiſe thee, who never ceaſeſt to bleſs us.</p>
                  <p>By the grace and merits of him, who finiſhed the grand works of eternal redemption for us, living and dying, to ſave us, Lord, make us live and dye thy ſervants, that we may be partakers of that happineſs, which by his blood he hath purchaſed for us, in the Kingdome of Bliſs. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:170533:100"/>
               <head>The ſeventh and laſt Word.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>LUKE 23.43.</bibl>
                     <p>Father in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy hands I commend my Spirit.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd well might he call him Father, becauſe he had merited the name of an obedient Son, to the laſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute of his life; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt worthy to gain at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. But here a doubt occures, what we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by the hands of God? are we with the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropomorphites</hi>
                  <pb n="191" facs="tcp:170533:100"/>to aſcribe the form and lineaments of man unto God,<note place="margin">Theod. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> as if he had eyes and ears, and hands, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts and faculties like unto us? far be it, for God is a ſpiritual ſubſtance, of an inviſible and indiviſible nature, without body, parts or paſſions, of infinite power, wiſdome and goodneſs: but for the better explanation of this, and the like expreſſion in holy Writ, we muſt make uſe of that known adage of the <hi>Hebrew Doctors, Lex loquitor linguam filiorum hominum.</hi> That is, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt in the Scripture deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cends to the capacity of man, ſpeaks man's language, that is, ſo, as he would be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by man; and therefore preſents him in the faculties of
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:170533:101"/>the mind of man, and in the lineament of the body of man, not that he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally either of them, for he is a moſt pure and a moſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple entitie without any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pority, or compoſition. And ſo, the hands of God, do denote unto us, his wiſdom and power, or which fals in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one meaning, his intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect knowing all things, and his will enabling all things, for with theſe two, as it were two hands, God did all things. The will of God is his power; for all things whatſoever he would, he did in heaven and earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Spirit,</hi> There are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſignifications of this word Spirit, in Scripture, which if not rightly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, may occaſion divers
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:170533:101"/>errours; it is ſpoken of God, or of Angels, or of men, or of inferiour creatures. Of God, it is ſpoken ſometimes Eſſentially, ſometimes Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally. <hi>God is a Spirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jo. 4.24.</note> 
                  <hi>and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit and truth.</hi> So alſo,<note place="margin">Iſai. 31.3.</note> So alſo, <hi>The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians are men, and not Gods, and their Horſes fleſh and not ſpirit;</hi> for if they were God, they were Spirit; ſo, God altogether, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in his eſſence, is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: but when the word Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is ſpoken not eſſentially of all, but perſonally of one, then that word deſigneth the holy Ghoſt.<note place="margin">Matth. 28, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Go and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize all in the Name of the Father, and Son, and the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.6.</note> 
                  <hi>And the Spirit
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:170533:102"/>it ſelf beareth witneſs,</hi> &amp;c. And as of God, ſo of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels alſo it is ſpoken in two reſpects of good Angels, ſent forth to miniſter for them that ſhall be heirs of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And evil Angels,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.14.</note> 
                  <hi>The lying Spirit that would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the King by the Prophet.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Kin. 22.22. Hoſea 4.8.</note> The ſpirit of whoredom, <hi>when the people asked counſel of their ſtocks:</hi> And <hi>ſpiritus vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiginis,</hi> the ſpirit of giddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or perverſities which the Lord doth mingle amongſt the people in his judgment. Of man alſo, is this word Spirit ſpoken two wayes; ſometimes for the Soul, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time for thoſe animal ſpirits which conſerve us in ſtrength and vigour,<note place="margin">Job 6.4.</note> 
                  <hi>The poyſon of Gods arrows drinketh up my
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:170533:102"/>ſpirit;</hi> and alſo for the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour faculties of the ſoul, in a regenerate man, as there, <hi>My Soul doth magnifie the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd, and my ſpirit rejoyceth in God my Saviour.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 1.47.</note> And then laſtly, of inferiour crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, it is taken two wayes too, of living creatures, <hi>The God of the Spirits of all fleſh;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 16.22.</note> and of creatures with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out life (other then a meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical life) as of the wind often:<note place="margin">Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k. 1.21.</note> 
                  <hi>And of</hi> Ezekiels <hi>wheeles; the ſpirit of life was in the wheeles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in this place, the Spirit of Chriſt may be taken either for his ſoul, which is the ſubſtantial form of the body, or for life it ſelf; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſpiration is a ſign of life; and they that breath,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:170533:103"/>live, and when the leave off to breath, they leave off to live. If by the ſpirit, we underſtand his ſoul, this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat muſt be had; we muſt not imagine that danger im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending to it, by leaving the body, as is uſual to dying men, who commend their ſouls in penſive ſupplications, becauſe they go to the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal of the Great Judg, to receive glory, or puniſhment. Such a commend his ſoul needed not, becauſe it was bleſt from its creation, as well in regard of its perſonal conjunction to the Son of God, as becauſe it left the body in a glorious triumph, being a terrour to whole Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of devils. So that in this ſenſe, the words imply
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:170533:103"/>no more, then that his ſoul which was formerly in the body, as in a Tabernacle, ſhould be depoſited in the hands of his father, until he be reſtored, when the time of reſtoring ſhould come; but it is more credible, that by the ſpirit, is here underſtood the corporal life, as the meaning may be this; I do now deliver the ſpirit of life, by which I do leave off to breath, and leave off to live, and this ſpirit, this life, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I commend to thee, that thou mayſt ſhortly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give it to my body; for with thee nothing periſheth, but all things live, who by calling thoſe things which are not, giveſt them a being, and thoſe things which do not live, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt them a life.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:170533:104"/>
               <p>And this conſtruction is moſt agreeable to the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt: <hi>Pull me out of the net,<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.4.</note> that they have laid pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily for me; for thou art my ſtrength, into thy hands I commend my ſpirit.</hi> Where by ſpirit is meant life, for he humbly beſeecheth the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, not to ſuffer him to periſh by the malice of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, but that he would preſerve his life; the like is evidenced out of thoſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical words.<note place="margin">Heb 5.7.</note> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Who, in the dayes of his fleſh, when he had offered up prayers and ſupplications, with ſtrong crying and tears, unto him that was able to ſave him from death, and was heard in that he feared.</hi>
                  </q> Theſe words cannot be referred to his
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:170533:104"/>prayer in the garden, as ſome interpret, for theſe,<note place="margin">Mark 14.</note> the Lord prayed not with a loud voice, neither was he, nor would he be heard, that he might be ſafe from death, but to ſhew that he had a natural deſire not to die, thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating himſelf to be a true man, whoſe nature ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors death; but they rather ſignifie that he deſired not to be ſwallowed up by death, and that he might only taſte of it, and ſo return to life. And in that he was heard; for he was not long detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the black vaults of the grave, but had a ſpeedy and a glorious reſurrection; So, that here the Lord was not troubled for his ſoul, for he knew that to be ſafe, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:170533:105"/>beatified from its crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by a viſion of God face to face, but he was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licit ous concerning his body, which ſeemed by the ſting of death, to be diſappointed of life, and therefore prayes that it might not long remain under its tyranny, and in that his requeſt was fully obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>Here then we may ſatisfy thoſe <hi>Hereticks</hi> (ſuch as the <hi>Cerdonites,</hi> the <hi>Euticheans,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Manicheans</hi> were) which brought Chriſt upon the ſtage to play a part, and ſay he was born, and lived, and dyed in <hi>Phantaſmate,</hi> in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parence only, and repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not really. For if he dyed not, where is the contract between him and
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:170533:105"/>his father, that Chriſt ought to ſuffer all this, and ſo enter into his Glory? is that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract void, and of none effect? where is the ratification of that contract in all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets? wherefore doth <hi>Eſay</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">Eſay. 5 3.4 9</note> Surely he hath born our ſorrows, and he made his grave with the wicked in his death: where is the conſummation, and the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of all this? doth not the Goſpel here ſay, And he bowed his head, and gave up the Ghoſt, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after this his laſt prayer? is that fabulous? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid; in vain had we all been created, if we had not a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation in his true death. Chriſt truly dyed ſo as was contracted, ſo as was prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied,
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:170533:106"/>ſo as was related. But this I may boldly affirm, that he did not die ſo, as other natural men dye; for there is this diſtinction between them. Chriſt dyed becauſe he would dye; other men admitted to the dignity of <hi>Martyrdome</hi> are willing to dye, but they dye by the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the executioners, they cannot bid their ſouls go out, and ſay I will dye, as he did: <hi>I lay down my life for my ſheep,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 10.15, 17, 18.</note> ſayes he: <hi>No man taketh it from me, I lay it down of my ſelf:</hi> And <hi>De facto,</hi> he did lay it down, he diddye, before thetorments could have extorted it from him: Many crucified men lived many dayes upon the Croſs: the theeves were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live,
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:170533:106"/>long after Chriſt was dead; and therefore <hi>Pilate</hi> wondered that he was already dead: his ſoul did not leave his body by force,<note place="margin">Mar. 15 44.</note> but becauſe he would, when and how he pleaſed. Beſides Chriſt was not ſubject to the law of death, which appertained only to them, who were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from <hi>Adam,</hi> by carnal and ſinful generation, he being miraculouſly conceived of a virgin, by the overſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing of the holy Ghoſt, and being he was not invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in a general rebellion, and ſo had not incurred Gods diſpleaſure, it follows, that he was not involved in the general penalty, and ſo needed not to have dyed by the rigour of any law, as we
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:170533:107"/>muſt. And then when out of his own pleaſure; and to advance our ſalvation, he would dye, yet he dyed ſo, as that though there were a diſunion of body and ſoul (which is truly death) yet there remained a nobler and faſter Union, the Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Union of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, to his body and ſoul: to this I add death hath that dominion over men, that they have no power to raiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from it; Chriſt had, for even in ſpight of death he retained in Almighty power, and delivered his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoul by a Victorious and Triumphant Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So then, as it is true, Chriſt Jeſus dyed, elſe none of us could live; ſo he dyed
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:170533:107"/>not as others dye: not by the neceſſity of any law, not by the violence of any exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner, nor by the ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his beſt ſoul, (if I may ſo call it) the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, nor by ſuch a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his natural and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſoul, as that he would not, or could not, nor did not reſume it again From what hath been premiſed, thou maiſt learn, O man, Firſt, How that Chriſt ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Power, his Wiſdom, and his Charity even then, when he ſeemed to be infirm and void of all conſolation. They who naturally dye, do by degrees looſe their voice and ſtrength, but he in the laſt paſſage of his diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, uſed a louder acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:170533:108"/>then formerly. And not only that, but as arguments of his further power, he cauſed the baſis of the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe to tremble, the ſtones to be cleft, the Sepulchres to be opened, and the vail of the Temple to be diſjoynted. All which want not their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral myſteries; as the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake and the Sciſion of the Rocks, ſignifieth that by the paſſion and death of Chriſt, men ſhould be moved to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and the obdurate hearts of the obſtinate ſhould be cut in pieces, as it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thoſe who went from this ſad ſpectacle,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.</note> ſtriking their breaſts; the apertion of the ſepulchres, denote the glorious reſurrection of the dead bodies, which were to
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:170533:108"/>be raiſed by vertue of his: The renting of the vail of the Temple, whereby the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum</hi> did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, did imply, that for the merits of Chriſts death, the Caeleſtial ſanctuary ſhould be opened, and that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhould be admitted to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the beatifical viſion.</p>
               <p>Neither did he ſhew his wiſdome only, in theſe ſhadowy Myſteries, but alſo in that he produced life out of death, which was typifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he made the water flow from the flin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty rock: And Chriſt for the ſame cauſe compared himſelf to a grain of wheat,<note place="margin">Numb. 20.8, 9.</note> that dying fructifieth abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Jo. 12.24.</note> for, as from the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that grain ſprouts a
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:170533:109"/>living ſtalk and eare, ſo from his death on the Croſs iſſued a life of grace to many nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; as the firſt man being gull'd with the ſweet apple, infected his whole poſterity with death, ſo the ſecond man ſwallowing the moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter apple of death, brought all, who were in him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, to eternal life. And what ſhall we ſay of his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which was divers wayes wonderfully demonſtrated at the inſtant of his death: His life, which was the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of all lives, the life of a King, the moſt powerful of all, the life of the wiſeſt, and beſt of all, the life of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, he voluntarily laid down for his enemies, for the wicked, for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful.
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:170533:109"/>From the flames of hell he frees them, that he might make them his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and Co-heirs, and empale them within the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed territories of heaven. Is there any then ſo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with cruelty to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo inſenſible of his own good, as not to enbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Chriſt with a thankful love? Is there any ſo negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of his own eternity, as not to embrace him with a ſweet recordation of his mercies? Lord melt our ſtony hearts, that they may take the impreſſions of ſuch divine and unſpeakable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here offers it ſelf alſo to our conſideration the great obedience of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:170533:110"/>to his heavenly father, in this recommendation of his ſpirit, to his paternal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, whereby is verified, what the Apoſtle ſayes,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.8.</note> 
                  <hi>That he humbled himſelf, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came obedient unto death, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the death of the Croſs.</hi> It was ſo admirable, that it had its imitation from his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conception, and without intermiſſion (like an indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible line) laſted to his very death. Neither was it deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated to one kind of work, but extended to all thoſe things, which it pleaſed his Father to command; to this do thoſe expreſſion of his tend,<note place="margin">Jo. 4.34. Jo. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>It is my meate to do his will that ſent me, and to finiſh his work. I came down from heaven not to do my own
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:170533:110"/>will, but his that ſent me.</hi> And becauſe (<hi>Quia per vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctimas aliena Caro, per obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientiam propria voluntas muctatur. Gregor. mor. l.</hi> 35. c. 11.) Obedience is the beſt of ſacrifices, therefore as many works as he did, during his peregrination on earth, ſo many moſt pleaſing ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices he offered to God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. Hence ſuch varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of them; that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we find him faſting in the deſart, and lodging with wild beaſts; ſometimes in the frequency of men, eating and drinking; ſometimes at home obſcure, and ſilent, and that not for few years; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times glorious, as well in wiſdome. as eloquence; and unclapſing his power of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:170533:111"/>miracles; ſometimes with great indignation, throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the buyers and ſellers out of the Temple: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (as it were) weak, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining from the company of the multitude; all which did require the noble qualities of an excellent ſoul, which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him no way ſubject to the ſwayes of any paſſionate will of his own. And as he pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, ſo he taught the rule of perfect Obedience. <hi>He that will follow me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 16.24.</note> 
                  <hi>let him deny himſelf.</hi> Man muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his own, before he can ſubmit to the will of Chriſt. The Celeſtial orbs do not reſiſt the Angels that move them, whether they be driven to the Eaſt, or to the Weſt, becauſe they have no proper propenſitie, either to
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:170533:111"/>one part of the heavens, or to the other, and the Angels themſelves are at Gods beck, to obſerve all his mandates, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no repugnancy between their wils and his but ſeem to be ſo happily conſolidated to him, as if they and he were but one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. And certainly if we will become Chriſts true diſciples, we muſt disband our own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and natural affections, and wholly reſign our ſelves to his diſpoſe, and ſo become one with him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And laſtly, We may make this benefit of this laſt prayer of the Lord, to uſe it, as a holy Ejaculation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all emergencies, more eſpecially at the hour of death; for if the ſoul, then leaving the body, fals into
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:170533:112"/>the clutches of the Devil,<note place="margin">Ab inferis nulla re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptio.</note> there is no poſſibility of its redemption (for as the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the <hi>Saints,</hi> ſo the torments of the damned are eternal) but if it happily comes into the paternal hands of God, the potency of enemies is not to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but it will be re-united to the body, and (both of them) ſhall in the end enjoy a bleſſed and a glorious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; And herein lyes an ocean of comfort to all believers, for as Chriſt the head did riſe, ſo ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very member of his myſtical body be raiſed from corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to incorruption,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 42, 43.</note> from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to glory. It is ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried of an Indian King, that when he had been Catechiſed
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:170533:112"/>ſo far in the articles of our Chriſtian Religion, as to come to the ſuffered, and crucified, and dead, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, impatient of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any father, asked only, is your God dead, and buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? then let me return to the worſhip of the Sun, for I am ſure, that will not die, whereas if he had but the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to learn the following Article, he might hear of his Triumphant Aſcenſion into heaven, and ſitting there in Majeſty and power on Gods right hand, all the conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Chriſtian conſiſts in this principally, that after a troubleſome warfare here, he ſhall be carried to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> boſome, the Celeſtial Paradiſe, to the durable Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:170533:113"/>to his Maſters joy, to an inheritance immortal, undefiled, reſerved in the heavens, to a reſt from his labours, and to behold the glory of God. O how it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves each man then, to ſecure his intereſt in thoſe felicities, and daily and hourly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his ſoul to that God that made it. We are all careful enough when death approaches, to put our houſes in order, and diſpoſe of our temporals, but few take a thought for that which is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual. We had rather with King <hi>Aſa</hi> ſeek to the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, then to the Lord,<note place="margin">2 Chr. 16.</note> when ſeized with ſickneſs; or with the Phariſees tithe mint and cummin, and leave the weighty Matters of the Law
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:170533:113"/>undone; but ſo we do but preſent God with maim, not perfect, with dead, not living ſacrifices: Nothing can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Kingdom of heaven, but what is pure and immaculate, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our chiefeſt care ſhould be, if we deſire to have admiſſion there, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſouls by true faith, and time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repentance, without which our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and tears will nothing avail; for without holineſſe no man ſhall ſee the face of God. He made our ſouls ſpirits, let us not then make them carnal, by feeding on corrupt luſt: He made them immortal, let us not murder them with our ſins, and deprive them of eternal life. He made them noble and after his own image, let us not make them bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh and earthly, by doting on the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and vanities of this tranſitory world. For what ſhal it profit a man to gain the whole world and loſe his own ſoul? or what ſhall a man give in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for his ſoul?</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="218" facs="tcp:170533:114"/>
                  <p>TO thee therefore, O thou Father of our Spirits, do we make our hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble addreſſes, that thou wouldſt be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be a Protector of our ſouls and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, both here and to all eternity.</p>
                  <p>Thou art our Rock, and our Fortreſſe, therefore for thy Names ſake defend and guide us.</p>
                  <p>We have no confidence in ſaints or Angels, for thou haſt charged the beſt of them with folly, but in the multitude of thy mercies, for thou alone haſt redeemed us, O Lord God of truth.</p>
                  <p>Thou that didſt ſhew thy power in weakneſs, and ſhake the foundations of the earth, when ſuffering on thy Croſs, make us to tremble through the horror of our ſins, and to fear thy judgments for them, which we juſtly merit.</p>
                  <p>As thou didſt then cleave the Rocks, and rend the vail of thy ſanctuary, ſo melt our ſtony hearts with the beams of thy grace, that they may receive the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of thy favors, and that we may enter into the Holy of Holies above,
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:170533:114"/>which thou haſt prepared for thy choſen.</p>
                  <p>The height of our love is but to lay down our lives for our deareſt relations, but thou didſt depoſe thy precious life for thy enemies that rebelled againſt thee.</p>
                  <p>Lord who by thy active and paſſive o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, wouldſt leave nothing undone or unſuffered for our ſalvation, O teach us to obey thy word, to embrace thy meti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; to practiſe what thou commandeſt</p>
                  <p>Let our wills be wholly reſolved into thine, and make us conformable to thee; as thy ſaints and angels in heaven are.</p>
                  <p>We confeſs, Lord, that the wages of ſin is deaeth, and that we juſtly deſerve to be reduced to our firſt nothing, but O let not death, which is the work of the divel, have dominion over thy creatures, who are the work of thine own hands.</p>
                  <p>Before we receive a ſummens to our end, we pray thee furniſh us with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite graces, that we may be clothed with the wedding garment of holineſſe and righteouſneſs, to meet thee the ſweet Bridegroom of our ſouls.</p>
                  <pb n="220" facs="tcp:170533:115"/>
                  <p>Let us not commend unto thee foul &amp; ſinful ſpouſes, but clean and ſorrowful ſpirits; for thou deſpiſeſt not, Lord, humble and contrite hearts.</p>
                  <p>At the hour of death, Lord, ſpeak comfortably to our ſouls, and ſeal in our hearts by thy holy Spirit, the pardon of all our ſins.</p>
                  <p>Aſſiſt us with thy preſence againſt all the aſſaults of our ſpiritual adverſaries for if thou wilt be with us, we ſhall nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fear nor feel any evil, though we walk through the valley of the ſhadow of death.</p>
                  <p>And grant, that though our ſouls and bodies be ſeparated by death for a ſhort ſpace, they may be re-united at thy great day, and by vertue of thy Reſurrection, be raiſed to live in thy ever bleſſed eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
                  <p>Grant this for his ſake who lived and dyed, and roſe again for our ſalvation, Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
